<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Looking Out To Sea]]></title>
  <link href="http://dougalstanton.github.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://dougalstanton.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-02-18T19:13:22+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://dougalstanton.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Dougal Stanton]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Five minutes everyday to turn the world upside down]]></title>
    <link href="http://dougalstanton.github.com/blog/2013/02/18/five-minutes-everyday/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-18T18:59:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://dougalstanton.github.com/blog/2013/02/18/five-minutes-everyday</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&#8217;ve been doing capoeira now for about two years I think, and
one thing that hasn&#8217;t really changed in that time is my complete
inability to do a handstand or a cartwheel.</p>

<p>Since the beginning of the year (you know, midway through January)
I&#8217;ve had an alarm on my phone that buzzes at 6.30pm <em>every single day</em>
and tells me I have to practise. Nearly every single day since I started I
have set aside five minutes to practise. I set a timer so that I don&#8217;t
do 3 minutes then decide that I&#8217;m probably done, and so that I stop at
5 minutes. The point is that it&#8217;s not supposed to be a burden or a
long gruelling exercise regime.</p>

<p>Five minutes practice every day &#8212; throwing myself up against a bare
wall initially, but slowly becoming more independent &#8212; has brought
about a massive change. I&#8217;m still not capable of busting out amazing
inverted moves but if I&#8217;d known two years ago that I could be where I
am now with only month of this I would be shocked.</p>

<p>I&#8217;ll continue to be shocked and I hope the improvements will continue
too.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Salvaging the Challenge]]></title>
    <link href="http://dougalstanton.github.com/blog/2013/02/17/salvaging-the-challenge/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-17T18:57:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://dougalstanton.github.com/blog/2013/02/17/salvaging-the-challenge</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Since losing the old blog host I&#8217;ve been trying to reclaim what I could
from the Wayback Machine, particularly archives of Helen&#8217;s blog.</p>

<p>There aren&#8217;t enough entries saved to cover the whole year, even if we
ignore the entries which aren&#8217;t part of the challenge. Which basically
means we&#8217;ve lost the record of the challenge and frankly I&#8217;m gutted by
this state of affairs.</p>

<p>I have 67 saved entries and there should be about 190, though some of
those will be links to the same article. This is still a lot of missing
posts.</p>

<p>At this point I&#8217;m beginning to wonder if saving those 67 is worth it.
I&#8217;m quite demoralised.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Migration to Octopress etc]]></title>
    <link href="http://dougalstanton.github.com/blog/2013/02/11/migration-to-octopress-etc/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-11T19:43:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://dougalstanton.github.com/blog/2013/02/11/migration-to-octopress-etc</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>After the loss of my old blog, which I hope to at least salvage
from the Wayback Machine at some point, I&#8217;ve moved over to using
Octopress which has the built-in advantage of backed-up posts.</p>

<p>I shouldn&#8217;t be able to lose it all again.</p>

<p>(What is it about backing up data? You never do it until you&#8217;ve
been burned once? I think that seems about right. Everyone is
invincible until the first time they are laid low.)</p>

<p>Soon I will get my domain redirected here, so while things are
interrupted they will not be interrupted forever.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
