<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title>Looking Out To Sea</title>
    <link href="http://dougalstanton.net/atom.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="http://dougalstanton.net" />
    <id>http://dougalstanton.net/atom.xml</id>
    <author>
        <name>Dougal Stanton</name>
        <email>blog@dougalstanton.net</email>
    </author>
    <updated>2014-08-05T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <entry>
    <title>How many bicycles is too many?</title>
    <link href="http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2014-08-05-how-many-bicycles-is-too-many.html" />
    <id>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2014-08-05-how-many-bicycles-is-too-many.html</id>
    <published>2014-08-05T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2014-08-05T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The saying goes that you always need one more bike than you have. Well, initially I didn’t think I needed a bike at all but that assumption turned out to be wrong<a href="#fn1" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref1"><sup>1</sup></a>. Since then I’ve been discovering the ways in which my one bikes can help me out. Commuting every day, taking less time and able to carry much more to and from work. Carrying incredible amounts of shopping easily from the supermarket to home. Going on holiday for a week in Islay and Arran entirely under our own steam. Jetting across town to meet people, visit places and get around quickly.</p>
<p>The <a href="http://www.velominati.com/the-rules/#12" title="You always need one more bike">incredibly serious Rules</a> tell us that we always need another bike and I’m slowly coming to the conclusion that when you own 1 bike you probably need 2. (I will hold off judgement on the full implication.) My current bike plays the role of the generalist very well but I’m looking to specialise a bit. My long term plan is essentially to split my current bike into two bikes — one playing the role of the heavy duty workhorse that will let me get the shopping, take a full load of panniers on the road and be equipped for long journeys. The other would play the role of something light and simple for local riding, when I just want to jump on the bike and go.</p>
<p>I’ve been conscious for some time that I don’t get to wear some of my clothes when I’m cycling. Cycling wear ends up meaning technical wear when I leave the house and I want to stop that. I don’t walk to the shops with hiking boots and a pole so why should I cycle with the equivalent? Now that’s not to say I actually do <a href="http://edinburghcyclechic.wordpress.com/" title="Because you don&#39;t have to wear Lycra">wear lycra to hop on the bike</a> —</p>
<p>To that end I’ve been looking at something a bit minimalist and more stylish. It doesn’t always have to be about hard work, after all. I really like the idea of slim single-speed bike with none of the mess that I have on my current bike to spoil the look. I fear in practise that things like weather, luggage, lights and so on will minimise the extent to which this can be achieved. We don’t all live in California… but I’ve been putting some thought to what it would mean if we did.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr />
<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>How did I go so long living in Edinburgh without a bike? Why did nobody grab me by the shoulders and tell me I was missing out? Getting the bus seemed a reasonable way to move around when I wasn’t just walking.<a href="#fnref1">↩</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>The Swedish author with the bolt from the blue</title>
    <link href="http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2014-06-25-swedish-bolt-from-the-blue.html" />
    <id>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2014-06-25-swedish-bolt-from-the-blue.html</id>
    <published>2014-06-25T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2014-06-25T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I’ve mentioned in the past being unimpressed with <em>The Girl with the Dragon Tattoo</em> and suspecting that the translation was a good chunk of the problem. I remember thinking that the prose seemed very cliched and relied heavily on hackneyed sayings that shouldn’t be a part of a well-written novel. Since we can hardly blame the author of the Swedish original for the clunky English phrasing we’ll have to point the finger at the translator.</p>
<p>Maybe you think I’m being unfair. While on holiday recently I had time to read the two sequels and got the same impression with them as I did with the original book. And since they’re fresh in my mind I still remember some of the dodgy phrases. Let’s see if I can demonstrate some problems.</p>
<p>The English translations seem very fond of describing sudden events in the same lumpen way. There’s a couple from the first book, though not the only ones.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The question came like a bolt out of the blue, but Berger did not seem the least bit surprised.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Forgive me for bothering you out of the blue, but I happened to be in St. Albans, and I tried to call you during the day.”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>From the sequel, <em>The Girl who Played with Fire</em>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>And then out of the blue she had destroyed him. She had struck back with a power and determination that he had not dreamed she possessed. She had humiliated him. She had tortured him. She had all but demolished him.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Hedström said nothing during the taxi journey from Slussen to Kungsholmen. He was in a daze from out of the blue ending up in a real police investigation. He glanced at Bohman, who was reading Armansky’s presentation again.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>And finally from <em>The Girl who Kicked the Hornet’s Nest</em></p>
<blockquote>
<p>“Annika… this isn’t the way I had planned to end my time at Millennium. In the middle of chaos. But the offer came like a bolt from the blue, and I can’t say no. I mean, it’s the chance of a lifetime. I got the offer just before Dag and Mia were shot, and there’s been such turmoil here that I buried it. And now I have the world’s worst guilty conscience.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>At 6:00 she paid her bill and walked to Lillian’s place on Olivedalsgatan. She punched in the door code her friend had given her. She stepped into the stairwell and was looking for a light switch when the attack came out of the blue. She was slammed up against a tiled wall next to the door. She banged her head hard, felt a rush of pain, and fell to the ground.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I think you begin to see what I’m talking about. You read these phrases — and others like “within a few minutes he would be dead as a door-nail” — and wonder to yourself what the translator and editor were doing. There are dozens like these and they often break the illusion. Who carefully describes a method of killing someone that will result in them being “dead as a door-nail”?</p>
<p>It gives hope for the rest of us. Between dodgy translations of Stieg Larsson and the top-notch output of Dan Brown there’s room for everyone in the airport thriller market, whether you can write or not.</p>]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Grammar of movement (reprise) &mdash; Contact Jam</title>
    <link href="http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2014-04-11-grammar-of-movement-reprise.html" />
    <id>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2014-04-11-grammar-of-movement-reprise.html</id>
    <published>2014-04-11T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2014-04-11T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last weekend I finally screwed my courage to the sticking place and went along to <a href="https://www.facebook.com/groups/493304847398335/" title="Glasgow Jam Facebook page">Glasgow Jam</a>, an afternoon of contact improvisation and artistic jamming of other kinds.</p>
<p><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Contact_improvisation" title="Contact improvisation described, if not defined">Contact improvisation</a> is a dance form in the loosest sense. Wikipedia describes it as postmodern dance, which doesn’t help much. It’s interesting to me because it’s like a particular aspect of capoeira (the close-contact floor movement) without the martial intent. You move around and over and through each other, maintaining contact and exploring the way in which two (or more) people can interact. It’s entirely unchoreographed so you can just get stuck in there. There was a four-year-old child at the session too; it’s easy to do something if you’re willing to let yourself be loose. It reminded me a great deal of trust/contact exercises I’ve done with various drama groups over the years.</p>
<p>The session lasted 3 hours without any particular structure after the warm-up period. People would dip in and out of the floor to take a break, get water, or even play instruments and paint as part of the “jam” experience. Apart from these off-the-cuff musical additions there was no soundtrack. We were dancing in silence which I found unsettling at times — and not easy to get into. There were also a lot of “serious” expressions from the participants; I really couldn’t tell whether enjoying oneself was verboten or whether this was just the face everyone used when they concentrated. Or maybe they were always bored when “contacting” with me…</p>
<p>The session provided exactly the challenges that I expected it would. In light of my <a href="2014-04-05-grammar-of-movement.html" title="Grammar of movement: getting stuck in a rut">previous reflections on being stuck in a movement rut</a>, this was a great activity to highlight where my assumptions are. I had initially been worried that my instinct from capoeira would sneak in and I would pull someone’s leg out from under them without thinking! Thankfully that part of my capoeira game didn’t cross over but lots of other parts did. My biggest problem was being very uncomfortable touching the ground and otherwise being put into a vulnerable position. I was continually conscious of my need to be planted and in control — in short, not to surrender my trust to my dance partner. It took me over an hour of work to become comfortable with sitting on the ground, if you can believe that.</p>
<p>This follows neatly what I had said previously about ungrammatical movements — I’m so ingrained in the capoeira way that even when I try it’s really hard to embrace touching the ground with other body parts. On top of that I often found myself being, if not openly hostile, then antagonistic. Instead of an improvised dance I was making it quite game-like to see how the other person would react. Again, I found this hard to avoid but I’m sure it got quite annoying after a while.</p>
<p>Ultimately I had some problems trying to determine who the jam was for. It was billed as a participant-only event. There was no viewing gallery and it wasn’t a show. So in that respect it was for the dancers themselves — but it seemed so serious. There was no emotional interaction between people: no laughing, no whoops, no eye contact, no talking. I would like to return and see if I can improvise these more than anything else.</p>]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Grammar of movement</title>
    <link href="http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2014-04-05-grammar-of-movement.html" />
    <id>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2014-04-05-grammar-of-movement.html</id>
    <published>2014-04-05T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2014-04-05T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I wrote recently about <a href="/posts/2014-02-17-critical-appraisal-from-the-inside.html" title="My thoughts on Phil&#39;s performance at Conflux PITCH">Phil’s performance at the Conflux PITCH event</a> and how I had a hard time writing a meaningful critical appraisal. One of the issues was seeing the capoeira inside his performance and not being able to see past that.</p>
<p>One of the other performers that day was <a href="http://www.iamscotthouston.com/" title="Scott Houston&#39;s home page">Scott Houston</a>. Superficially he appears to share a lot of the same movements but it appears from his biography online that he has no capoeira training. He’s probably come across capoeira but it’s not a meaningful part of his background. Can we tell this by watching the way he moves? I think we can and it’s most obvious in this video, <em>Alive</em>.</p>
<iframe width="560" height="315" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/oBh7ASo1UIE" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>

<p>Like learning a language you pick up a great deal of capoeira through imitation rather than explicit instruction. The challenge of anyone learning capoeira or anything else by imitation is learning to identify what are the real rules and what are just things which your role models don’t do — things which you can’t learn by imitation because you don’t have anyone to imitate<a href="#fn1" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref1"><sup>1</sup></a>. Like a language, capoeira has a “grammar” and much of it is learned implicitly. After a while we all begin to speak (or move) in ways which are in tune with what we’re doing — the grammar becomes internalised and we no longer think “does this sound/feel right?”.</p>
<p>I think one of the main differences between Phil and Scott’s performances was that Phil has the capoeira grammar deep in his movement and has to struggle more to overcome that. (I predict that if I had any knowledge of gymnastics or Shotokan Karate then I might see their influence on Scott Houston’s movement. Any takers?) The director/ choreographer who spoke at the Conflux event mentioned specifically that he likes using artists outside their comfort zone to avoid the ingrained behaviours from taking over. Dancers always end up standing in the classic ballet postures — toes pointed, arms slight bent. Gymnasts have their own favoured postures and so on with all the other physical performance artists. Using people who haven’t been trained specifically produces a looseness of interpretation — at least according to this director’s opinion.</p>
<p>From the perspective of someone trying to learn capoeira this is also important. The movement culture in Scotland and Brazil is different — Scottish dance and Brazilian dance emphasise very different things in posture, for example. Unlearning the way in which we move and hold our bodies is almost even harder — I’ve been standing and walking this way in this mould my entire life, since I was old enough to imitate the movement of my parents. Seeing total capoeira beginners with experience of other movement forms brings other fascinating layers to the mix — whether they’ve done Taekwondo or belly dancing the outcome is something bold and original. And bringing something new to it is what we should all strive for!</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr />
<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>This is why I think it’s really important to have many role models in a class. Different people of different shapes and sizes who have different preferences for the ways in which they move — not only do you see a wider range of possibilities from which to synthesise your own style but you can also see how people play to their strengths and overcome their weaknesses — be it fitness, height, strength, or something else.<a href="#fnref1">↩</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Getting rid of bikes. Is that even allowed?</title>
    <link href="http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2014-03-30-getting-rid-of-bikes.html" />
    <id>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2014-03-30-getting-rid-of-bikes.html</id>
    <published>2014-03-30T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2014-03-30T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Ha! In direct contravention of <a href="http://www.velominati.com/the-rules/#12" title="Rule 12">rule number twelve</a> we just got rid of two bikes. That probably means the number of bikes we need stands at N+2 just to reach parity with where we were yesterday. We do have a lot more space in the hallway now, which is nice!</p>
<p>The decluttering is part one (the easy part) of preparations to move back to Edinburgh. More on that as we get closer to the departure point.</p>
<p>The bikes — Helen’s old bike and my old bike — went to the Glasgow Bike Station. My bike was bought from the Edinburgh Bike Station a few years ago to see if cycling would be a reasonable addition to my commute. Since then there was been no looking back (well, except to check traffic over my shoulder). Helen’s old bike was won by her gran in a raffle and she’s had it over fifteen years! So it was a more important moment to pass her bike on.</p>
<p>Riding down there was really scary, which surprised me. The whole feel of the bike which used to be my daily transport was totally alien because I’d not used it for more than a year. The geometry was odd. The handlebar felt too short, the position of the pedals was different and the circle they made seemed smaller than my current bike. The pedals were simple platforms and I kept trying to adjust my foot position as if there were toe traps. On top of that the brake blocks were pretty close to the nub so I wasn’t in the least confident that I could really pull off an emergency stop if required. Helen nearly fell off before starting, by instinctively reaching for drop bars which didn’t exist and tipping through the bike! But we both made the journey in one piece and walked away for afternoon tea at The Hidden Lane Tea Room.</p>
<p>The Bike Station will be able to refurbish or cannabalise the bikes as necessary and sell on bikes to more people, like me, looking for a cheap bike to get around.</p>
<p>I’ll have to think about what the N+2 might be for another blog post…</p>]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>I keep trying to not fall over and it's mostly a success</title>
    <link href="http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2014-03-13-i-keep-trying-to-not-fall-over.html" />
    <id>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2014-03-13-i-keep-trying-to-not-fall-over.html</id>
    <published>2014-03-13T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2014-03-13T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>That’s me completed Day 4 of skiing classes morning and afternoon. Yesterday I felt a significant amount of thigh pain. My hands and wrists are generally quite stressed from gripping on to ropes and pulling mechanisms as well as hefting skis. I’m definitely putting too much effort and muscle into these manoeuvres but I’m still scared it will all go wrong and I’ll tumble. I think I’d rather be the person with sore arms at the end of the day than the person who gets detached from the button lift and has to return to the bottom while the rest of the group wait patiently at the top. (My French small-talk hasn’t improved a great deal.)</p>
<p>Apart from pain in a number of interesting places I will try to list what I have discovered about myself, the learning process, skill lessons and so on.</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Being able to do something and being able to teach it are two different things. The two instructors I have had, Jean-Luc and Phillipe, have been great. They can spot whether you’re leaning wrong, twisting your body funny or occasionally doing something different unconsciously then explain why you’re doing it. The instructor in the level one class that I took once was not nearly as helpful but just gave orders — « ski parallèle ! » “Aye, but how?”</p></li>
<li><p>And by the same token both instructors have been really friendly. I’m the only English-speaker in one of my classes and I try to follow along as much as possible. But they’re very friendly and Jean-Luc in particular will try to translate any jokes and talk to me.</p></li>
<li><p>I’m really glad I’ve been cycling and doing capoeira for long enough to get reasonable control of my body. Sometimes this results in what we might euphemistically call “dynamic balance” (ie, I’m totally all over the shop but if I keep flailing I can stay on my feet). This is much better than just losing it! But not quite the picture of poise and elegance that my instructors exhibit.</p></li>
<li><p>There are plenty of really shallow runs that have steep lips that put me off but once I’m over them it’s all fine. That initial push over the lip is still very scary! Another scary thing is routes that have drop-off edges — one in particular is a snow-covered mountain road that is used during the summer time for the Tour de France. And like any winding mountain path there’s a sheer wall on one side and a sheer drop on the other. On any other route down I’d be perfectly capable of using the full width of the piste but somehow the idea that I might just fly off the edge is too much.</p></li>
<li><p>The colour markings on the routes seem pretty much invisible to me. All I can see are the red padding around the chairlift pylons and I can tell you that not every route is a red! The actual routes are marked with thin bits of painted wood that all basically look alike. Seriously, get your nonsense together. Combined with the non-obvious piste maps and the possibility that you find yourself at the top of a hill that you’re incapable of skiing down can be pretty paralysing. Every time I board a lift I have to ask myself “have I been this way before with an instructor?” and then the follow-up “did we have to take a special (non-obvious) route down to avoid the scary bits?”. It can really take the enjoyment out of it.</p></li>
<li><p>Did I mention the awful piste maps? Thankfully <a href="http://openpistemap.org" title="Piste maps made by user GPS submissions">Open Piste Map</a> comes to the rescue, but that shouldn’t be necessary. The others tell me that it’s not just Les Gets but <em>all</em> piste maps that have this ropey relation to actual geography while pretending to represent it. If it was either entirely symbolic (like the London Underground map) or entirely topological (like an OS map) it would be fine but they’re the worst of both. The distances aren’t accurate and the directions of lines don’t match up but the whole thing is overlaid on a fake isometric landscape that looks like it should relate to the landscape.</p></li>
<li><p>I’m not great at pushing myself to the front of the queue but frankly being at the end can be dangerous to one’s health. It’s much easier to follow the line of the instructor from just behind them than several people back with a timid skiier immediately in front. Lately we’ve been doing things which require more speed and being trapped behind a nervous person makes it much harder to pull them off without injury or loss of dignity.</p></li>
</ul>]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Someone put a massive mountain there</title>
    <link href="http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2014-03-09-someone-put-a-massive-mountain-there.html" />
    <id>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2014-03-09-someone-put-a-massive-mountain-there.html</id>
    <published>2014-03-09T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2014-03-09T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Situation report from the scene, live as it happens! It’s 6pm on the end of my first day in the French Alps. The sun was bright and if the weather continues like this I’m going to be wearing a lot less on the slopes than I initially thought.</p>
<p>I spent the morning and afternoon with <a href="http://www.esf.net" title="Ecole du ski francais">École du Ski Français</a> as an “adulte debutant” — ie, adult beginner. I’m slowly dredging up bits of French and learning new words (<em>batons</em> for ski poles and <em>casque</em> for helmet). The instructors would translate things into English but on many occasions it wasn’t necessary.</p>
<p>For lunch I had croque monsieur, frites avec mayonnaise and biere. Again I tried to be quite confident and the words more or less made sense to everyone so that’s quite good.</p>
<p>It seems unlikely I will be able to co-ordinate a lunchtime meeting with Helen and her family as I’m totally without phone service both in the village and in the mountains. Hopefully we’re organise something in advance one day, although at the moment I’m still pretty much clueless about getting around. It’ll have to be a really obvious and central meeting point or I won’t have a clue.</p>]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Capoeira introductory sessions</title>
    <link href="http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2014-03-07-capoeira-introductory-sessions.html" />
    <id>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2014-03-07-capoeira-introductory-sessions.html</id>
    <published>2014-03-07T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2014-03-07T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A few weeks ago during Edinburgh University’s study week there was an institution-wide focus on “innovative learning” and through a roundabout reasoning the foreign-language department asked Mão No Chão to put on a capoeira demonstration. We rarely get total new-comers through the door in our class in Glasgow so it’s been a very long since I looked round the room and saw so many people getting to grips with the basic movements of capoeira. And what an interesting experience that was!</p>
<p>I’ve been training with Mão No Chão for about 4 years but I feel like I’ve not got much to show for that. I can’t really do anything impressive. Yet looking round the room at the newcomers that day I really saw how far I’d come and how difficult (to them) even the simplest movements seemed to be. These were all intelligent and capable adults who struggled immensely with moving on all fours and keeping a solid base while in a lunge posture. I think if anyone doubts how far they have come when learning something like capoeira they should watch some real beginners — not to laugh but to really <em>see</em> all the subtle details that they’ve internalised and have now become second nature.</p>
<p>The second aspect that really came out was how much Eastern martial arts still dominates the public understanding of martial arts. Karate is still the last word when it comes to what a <em>martial art</em> means. From that idea two notions follow. One is that what is taught in a dojo while wearing a gi <em>is</em> the definition of martial arts. The traditional European styles of boxing, fencing or wrestling are something else — probably sports — but whatever they are they don’t count. Anything which doesn’t match the karate mould isn’t martial arts at all. From this comes a second idea that any thing which doesn’t relate in some way to Eastern martial arts is odd or unusual. If we regard the Eastern martial arts as the archetype rather than a variant then anything which varies in a different direction will be seen as very strange indeed.</p>
<p>Taking all that into account really complicates any explanation of what capoeira really is. The idea that something could be a game and a ritual and a martial art with a music component all at once — and that all of these antagonistic influences could be produce something coherent — was very confusing. I don’t believe we really managed to explain anything clearly.</p>]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Jane Eyre and norovirus: the truth they don't want you to know</title>
    <link href="http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2014-02-27-jane-eyre-and-norovirus%3A-the-truth.html" />
    <id>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2014-02-27-jane-eyre-and-norovirus%3A-the-truth.html</id>
    <published>2014-02-27T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2014-02-27T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="figure">
<img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3526/3767252642_51c7de05e7.jpg" alt="Pickwick the Dodo" /><p class="caption">Pickwick the Dodo</p>
</div>
<p>Several years ago I was reading <em>Jane Eyre</em> while staying at a friend’s house prior to us all attending a wedding nearby. The night before the wedding I was very ill — and spent the night vomiting loudly to prove it. The next day while the others were at the wedding I lay in bed, dozing and reading my book.</p>
<p>After book group this weekend I decided to re-read <em>The Eyre Affair</em>, a comedy detective novel which uses <em>Jane Eyre</em> as a principal plot point. On Tuesday morning I was again violently ill and spent the next day in bed, drifting in and out of sleep and reading.</p>
<p>Now I don’t want to start pointing fingers or naming names here but there’s something quite suspicious about all this and in future I’ll be laying off <em>Jane Eyre</em> and <em>Jane Eyre</em> derivatives for the sake of my health.</p>]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Critical appraisal from the inside</title>
    <link href="http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2014-02-17-critical-appraisal-from-the-inside.html" />
    <id>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2014-02-17-critical-appraisal-from-the-inside.html</id>
    <published>2014-02-17T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2014-02-17T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>On Tuesday we were at PITCH, an evening of new modern dance and related arts put on by <a href="http://www.conflux.co.uk/" title="Conflux Scotland, street art and physical theatre">Conflux Scotland</a>. The specific reason we knew about the event was because <a href="https://www.facebook.com/shady.phil.7" title="Shady Phil on Facebook">Shady Phil</a> (or <a href="https://www.facebook.com/spottedstripescircus" title="Spotted Stripes Circus">one of his other guises</a>, at least) was performing a piece.</p>
<p>After each performance of acrobatics/dance/drama there was space in the timetable to fill in feedback forms, and we were heavily encouraged to complete them. The specific intent of the evening was getting new and less-established artists a bit of publicity so feedback from the public was a bit part of it.</p>
<p>I really struggle when it comes to providing constructive feedback in most circumstances but when it’s someone I know doing something I’m slightly familiar with then nothing seems right. I start providing feedback on my own opinions, trying to analyse them as much as the thing in front of me — “would I say this to a stranger?”, “would I think that if I didn’t know the person?”. This is the trap I spring on myself.</p>
<p>The Bene Gesserit <em>Litany against Fear</em> comes to mind for some reason:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Fear is the mind killer. Fear is the little-death that brings total obliteration.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>In this case not fear but introspection. Introspection is the mind killer. Introspection is the little-death that brings total indecision.</p>
<p>With anyone else I can say “oh she’s doing a bit of body popping” or “this is a bit odd” or “where do they find this weird music?” but when it’s someone I know these thoughts feel like betrayals. They come through as “oh he’s doing his capoeira thing again” or “was that meant to happen?” and I can’t enjoy the work for what it is.</p>
<p>My apologies to Phil for not completing the feedback or coming up with anything to say in person. I did enjoy the piece and the character made me think of several things — of puppets, of possession, of mistreated beasts – but I couldn’t really articulate any of these things at the time. Whether the story that I constructed in my head was the story you constructed in yours I don’t know; but it formed in my head all the same, which is important. I definitely can’t say that about all the pieces that night.</p>
<p>Here’s a bit of <a href="https://www.facebook.com/spottedstripescircus" title="Spotted Stripes Circus">Phil and Spotted Stripes Circus</a> to enjoy!</p>
<iframe width="560" height="315" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/lAsZVDFUcaQ" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>

]]></summary>
</entry>

</feed>
