<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>Looking Out To Sea</title>
        <link>http://dougalstanton.net</link>
        <description><![CDATA[A blog of sorts, unsorted.]]></description>
        <atom:link href="http://dougalstanton.net/rss.xml" rel="self"
                   type="application/rss+xml" />
        <lastBuildDate>Sun, 28 Jul 2013 00:00:00 UT</lastBuildDate>
        <item>
    <title>Cord&atilde;o de Ouro capoeira with CM Papa Leguas</title>
    <link>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2013-07-28-cdo-capoeira-with-cm-papa-leguas.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>Recently Contra Mestre Papa Leguas of Cordao de Ouro was invited to teach sessions in Edinburgh and Glasgow by <a href="http://www.cdoscotland.com/" title="Cordao de Ouro Scotland">CDO Scotland</a>. I attended one of the 3-hour classes in Glasgow to expand my experience a bit and see what other groups do when they’re being taught in their own style.</p>
<p>(I have previously been to large workshops organised by Malungos and Senzala but the guest teacher has been an Angola Mestre — Camaleao and Carlao respectively. This was a different circumstance because the teacher was definitely “something different”.)</p>
<p>The training room in Wellington Church on the corner of Southpark Avenue and University Avenue is a nice venue. Very clean and neat with some kind of textured vinyl-like flooring. I arrived and met a few people that I knew from training in Edinburgh and the regular open roda that we have to raise money for charity.</p>
<p>The class started with a discussion about body mechanics. The example was “to do an <em>au</em> you must throw your hips in the air, not put your hands on the ground” because “to do an <em>au sem mao</em> you must throw your hips in the air not throw your head at the ground” (paraphrased). I found this interesting and was looking forward to some biomechanical-oriented teaching which I think would help me a lot. Sadly it didn’t appear.</p>
<p>We did some plenary work on ginga and faking a rabo de arraia and spinning away again. Looking round the room I wasn’t the only person failing to see what he was actually doing, as he wasn’t describing the moves and he was executing them too fast to really follow.</p>
<p>This sequence built up into something longer, tacking on other moves which were also poorly understood. This was one of the defining moments of the class for me. Some of the sections were aimed at quite proficient players and the group as a whole didn’t reflect that. If it had been a trainers session rather than an open/all-levels session it would have been understandable.</p>
<p>The pairs work was similarly odd — maybe more for me than other people, I don’t know. I’m trying to be objective and subjective at the same time. Or at least subjective with the knowledge that I don’t want to come across as believing “they do it differently so they must be wrong”.</p>
<p>At the end was a split roda (one bateria, two simultaneous games) so everyone could have a few fun games to finish off. The music was something that took me a bit by surprise. The tempo was fast-paced and the singing didn’t match the rhythm at all. I think it would have been hard to match the speed of the bateria actually. This in particular was very alien to me.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 28 Jul 2013 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2013-07-28-cdo-capoeira-with-cm-papa-leguas.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Another rainy Traquair Fair</title>
    <link>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2013-07-28-another-rainy-traquair-fair.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>I’m just back from another Traquair Fair. I went to my first Traquair Fair two years ago and it rained quite heavily. There wasn’t one last year but in case I thought the 2011 rainfall was a freak occurence it happened again. Rain, wet tents, muddy dancing and drinking cider in the dark. We must be getting old though — no midnight trip to the maze.</p>
<p>We played some capoeira on the Saturday while the sun was beating down. We had a reasonable crowd at one point though they still wouldn’t “crowd” us. Even when we want them to form a tight circle around the action everyone hides off to the side. We need to concentrate on “street performance banter” to rally crowds and tell them what to do, where to sit and how to enjoy themselves. I think that would make for a more meaningful show.</p>
<p>So while we were programmed for a “Capoeira Dance Workshop” we ended up with a ninety minute capoeira game with some crowd interaction and an attempt to get people to clap or even sing. Enjoyable, especially on the lawn in the sun, in front of Traquair House, but not what it <em>could</em> have been.</p>
<p>The rains held off until we were finished and packing the instruments back up. The deluge when it came was pretty all-consuming though…</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 28 Jul 2013 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2013-07-28-another-rainy-traquair-fair.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Jurassic Park: airport fiction when dinosaurs ruled the bestsellers</title>
    <link>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2013-07-25-jurassic-park-airport-fiction.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>As a little chap I distinctly remember enjoying Jurassic Park on the big screen. I think it was one of those defining blockbuster movies of my youth, like everybody remembers seeing Star Wars for the first time. And in some sense it was just as revolutionary for the use of computer graphics. Those dinos looked <em>real!</em></p>
<p>The book is a proper disappointment, falling squarely into the category of stories that get much better when translated to film. Michael Crichton was a prolific writer of works that would eventually get adapted to the screen — maybe they all needed someone else to clean up his terrible dialogue?</p>
<p>Whenever I read a book now I come back to Christopher Brookmyre’s BDQ:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>I’ll swallow any scenario, as long as the film sticks to its own bullet-deadliness quotient.</p>
<p>An action film establishes its own rules of gunplay. In some, every bullet is potentially lethal — even the old shot to the shoulder can look worryingly near to the upper-chest area. But in others, machine guns can seem the least deadly weapon known to man. To illustrate, at one end of the spectrum there’s your Tarantino movies: reputations aside, there’s not that much gunplay, so when somebody lets off a shot, it’s for real, and it’s usually fatal. High bullet-deadliness quotient. At the other end, there’s your John Woo movies: zillions of rounds goin’ off an’ the only thing they ever hit is glass. Low bullet-deadliness quotient. In a high BDQ film, if the baddie draws a bead on somebody, get ready for ketchup. In a low BDQ film, that’s just a bad day for the janitor. And both types are fine by me, as long as the rules are followed consistently.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The issue of consistency in suspension of disbelief is paramount. It is the downfall of many a bad movie. <em>Prometheus</em>, for example, repeatedly set up characters as leaders in their field who made basic mistakes. in a high technology world which was simultaneously less capable than our own.</p>
<p>Jurassic Park has these failings and more besides. There are a number of “experts” in paleontology, genetics, mathematics and zoo management who have manage to come out with some real howlers. Geneticists who can’t remember where they got their DNA from. Park management who can’t remember how to reboot the park management system after it fails.</p>
<p>What really gets my goat is the inconsistency in character. From one scene to the next characters will change personality drastically so that the stupid thing they do to move the plot along seems reasonable. The nine year-old girl who was rocking back and forth in terror is now complaining about lack of ice cream or wanting to play with the walkie-talkie. In case it had escaped your attention there’s a velociraptor in the hallway. But the plot dictates the raptor find the kids so rather than stay quiet and frightened they have to squabble over who gets to play with this new toy.</p>
<p>This inconsistency appears again and again, and each time it does the urge to fling the book across the room rises. Frankly, they should all have been eaten.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Thu, 25 Jul 2013 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2013-07-25-jurassic-park-airport-fiction.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>First time taking a capoeira class</title>
    <link>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2013-07-18-first-time-taking-a-capoeira-class.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>Today, through an unfortunate series of events, both Piolho and Nick were unavailable to teach the class — Piolho we knew all along wouldn’t make it but Nick had to work late out of town.</p>
<p>The unfortunate part comes where not one but two new people arrive at the group. I ended up leading most of the class with some aid from Simon and Stephen. On the bright side new folk were from the Glasgow Senzala group and had done capoeira before. Everyone was able to follow along with my garbled instructions and wooly attempts to explain.</p>
<p>Most of the class was spent going over very basic stuff which was nice. They were used to a different kind of capoeira, so they could use that to get familiar with the style and I wasn’t too taxed coming up with crazy sequences and variations. We spent a good amount of time on the ginga, because it’s something we all need to work on, endlessly, and it’s something that is very different between Senzala and Mao No Chao.</p>
<p>In the end I enjoyed myself and I think everyone felt they had worked up a good sweat and didn’t seem too angry that they weren’t getting a teacher with a plan and a system!</p>
<p>The class was the opposite of what I’d been looking forward to, as I’d wanted to work more on the music stuff and had been trying to practise a basic samba rhythm on the pandeiro while waiting outside. But that is not how things fell out.</p>
<p>So I hope to see them again in future and if I ever have to teach a class again I’ll maybe have something in the back of my mind.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Thu, 18 Jul 2013 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2013-07-18-first-time-taking-a-capoeira-class.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Cooking by ratios: the book</title>
    <link>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2013-07-13-cooking-by-ratios-the-book.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>I’m not a great cook and very much envy the just-throw-stuff-together style of cookery which some people have. The exacting sciences of mixed drinks and bread baking provide some solace for me, because they’re all about the correct mixing of ingredients in well defined ratios.</p>
<p>It seems obvious that a book called <em>Ratio: The Simple Codes Behind the Craft of Everyday Cooking</em> would be something right up my street. Michael Ruhlman attempts to argue that much more of cooking follows rules of proportion and ratio — and that lack of emphasis on this fact leaves people slavishly following recipes without understanding the fundamentals. Each subtle variation is a “new” recipe.</p>
<p><em>Ratio</em> is his solution: a book of recipes by proportion. His introduction stipulates the important rule that ratios should be understood by weight not volume because the quantity of dry ingredients will vary a lot when packed. The cornflakes rule: contents may settle during transit.</p>
<p>We’re barely out of the starting blocks before he starts breaking his rules. Flour in cups, butter in sticks (what?), broccoli in cups…</p>
<p>Then we get to the cake chapter and he flat out says — the ratio isn’t important! The proportions of sponge and pound cake are identical! So we’re less than a fifth into the book and he’s already working hard to demolish his whole argument.</p>
<p>I didn’t follow any of the recipes though some of them looked dubious. Other people who read the book before me thought his pastry was totally wrong. But right or not, I didn’t come away feeling that I understood the ingredients at any deeper level. His recipes were just as confusing as if they’d been given as predefined measures. Apart from a dartboard-style diagram on the front cover there weren’t any useful charts to explain how the recipes related to each other and the proportions and ingredients used.</p>
<p>Starting again from scratch — with a more technical approach to the subject and a more discriminating eye for the examples — and this book could be a real winner. I really wanted to like it, but so many things annoyed me.</p>
<p>To take a contrasting example, <em>Dough</em> by Richard Bertinet uses the same approach to ratios but devotes an entire book to (in essence) just one ratio: ten parts flour to seven parts water. In <em>Dough</em> the technical detail is omitted because there are so many examples. <em>Ratio</em> has neither technical explanation nor deep coverage, but instead flits from chapter to chapter.</p>
<p>If there are other treatments of this topic out there I would be interested to hear what they’re like.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sat, 13 Jul 2013 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2013-07-13-cooking-by-ratios-the-book.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>I barely even read email any more</title>
    <link>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2013-05-29-i-barely-even-read-email-any-more.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>I’m subscribed to a handful of mailing lists for projects and programming languages that I have worked with in the past. I receive stuff from the usual online sellers plus the newsletters of local theatres, venues and community groups.</p>
<p>Every single one of these gets deleted without even being opened. Why am I bothering to receive them? Why, in fact, do I even sign up for them in the first place?</p>
<p>I think I will go on an unsubscribing spree to reduce the load. Ideally I would like all my email to come directly into my main inbox (rather than being pre-filtered into other folders) but that everything in there to be directly relevant to me. And the vast majority of it from people I actually know in real life.</p>
<hr />
<p>Edit: After a couple of days of following the unsubscribe option for everything that came into my inbox it’s all looking much nicer already. And most sites don’t require you to remember a password to remove yourself from their mailing list, which is a bonus.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Wed, 29 May 2013 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2013-05-29-i-barely-even-read-email-any-more.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Star Trek Into Darkness a spectacle but nothing more</title>
    <link>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2013-05-27-star-trek-into-darkness-a-spectacle-but-nothing-more.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>We saw <em>Star Trek Into Darkness</em> last night, the second film since Hollywood decided to restart the series by showing us young Kirk, young Spock etc, before the events of the original television series. In fact, the film ends at the beginning of the “five year mission” that is part of the opening monologue for <em>Star Trek</em>.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/matthewsheean/3636722887/"
title="Star Trek Guys by Matthew Sheean, on Flickr"><img
src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3390/3636722887_713cbdf8f8.jpg"
width="323" height="500" alt="Star Trek Guys"
style="float:left;margin-right:10px;"></a></p>
<p>This film was disappointing for many insubstantial reasons. Much of the scenes were lifted from previous Star Trek — if you know your lore you’ll be guessing (correctly) how scenes unfold from the opening lines. So, heavy nods to the fans on this one, but for no particular reason.</p>
<p>Also, the bad guys in this were a bit underdeveloped. John Harrison, the spy played by Benedict Cumberbatch (Hollywood’s English-bad-guy <em>du jour</em>: move over Alan Rickman), is another nod to the fans<sup><a href="#fn1" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref1">1</a></sup> and a well-known character, though it’s getting to the point that some people have so many “origin stories” that they’re no longer discrete people. They are personality probability functions which depend on the observer to show something new at each moment. Some stories make full use of this — the Joker eventually made a career of lying about how he got his smile — but when everybody starts doing it the novelty quickly wears thin.</p>
<p>I was not angry at the story like I was angry coming away from <em>Prometheus</em> but they could certainly have made a more coherent tale. They spent so long in the last film bringing together the crew we know and love. This film made an inexpert attempt to drive a wedge between them but some of the premises were so hamfisted (the world’s weakest lovers’ tiff between Spock and Uhura) that I was bored of the attempts.</p>
<p>Who else has seen it? Any humble opinions?</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr />
<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>I’m trying not to give spoilers here so bear with me.<a href="#fnref1">↩</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Mon, 27 May 2013 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2013-05-27-star-trek-into-darkness-a-spectacle-but-nothing-more.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Capoeira workshop in Drumnadrochit</title>
    <link>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2013-05-27-capoeira-workshop-in-drumnadrochit.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>At the weekend I was up north with Helen and a number of other people from <em>Mão no Chão Capoeira Angola</em>. The <a href="http://www.diondragas.com" title="Dion&#39;s home page">group’s founder, Dion</a>, was over from Greece to take the weekend workshop.</p>
<p>We took a car up on Friday, leaving only two hours behind schedule (a record of punctuality where we are concerned). I had enough time to bake a loaf of bread to take, but not enough space in the car to pack a tent. We even had some of the half-done berimbaus from the instrument-making session strapped to the roof rack.</p>
<p>We drove to Inverness, gathered some supplies and then switched south again on the other side of Loch Ness to Drumnadrochit for pizza and chips before heading to Fraser’s house on the shore of Loch Meiklie. Helen got the train into Inverness and we picked her up later that evening.</p>
<p>We all slept on the floor of Fraser’s living room that night because it was too wet to think about putting the tent up. I didn’t find the sleeping bag and mat much of a problem and slept reasonably well. I think I was woken by a slobbery dog on at least one of the days — the perils of lying on the ground.</p>
<p>After a lazy breakfast we put some more work into the instruments we’d brought with us. Then it was a bit of lunch and down to Glenurquhart Public Hall in Drumnadrochit for the Saturday afternoon of training. In the evening Fraser’s wife brought down big pans full of curry and rice which we had in the hall, in the well-appointed kitchen attached. If you’re looking for a venue up that way I can really recommend it on facilities (I have no idea how much it cost).</p>
<p>I was still quite sore from my mysterious muscle injury in my side (see previous post) — I wouldn’t work out what it was until the Sunday — so I was taking things easy and not doing a lot of the inverted stuff or anything which required stretching my arms behind me. Which is unfortunate because there was a heavy emphasis on <a href="http://cs.i.uol.com.br/album/1108_capoeira_f_024.jpg" title="Ponte, that is, bridge">ponte</a> which is basically all about being inverted, stretching arms behind you and taking your weight on them.</p>
<p>After class and the meal Helen and I nipped round the village to get some air and stopped in at <a href="http://www.fiddledrum.co.uk/" title="Restaurant and more">Fiddlers</a> for a sly half pint — sitting in the beer garden in what was left of the sunshine.</p>
<p>In the evening we stayed up drinking and watching crazy videos on YouTube of handbalancing, Cyr wheels and people who jump off cliffs without a safety net.</p>
<p>After lunch the next day we went to Drumnadrochit with everyone else and while they settled in for the second session of the weekend we boarded the (expensive) bus to Inverness to catch our train to Edinburgh and see Paper Aeroplanes at the Voodoo Rooms (a very fine gig).</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Mon, 27 May 2013 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2013-05-27-capoeira-workshop-in-drumnadrochit.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Pain in all the diodes down my left side</title>
    <link>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2013-05-15-pain-in-all-the-diodes.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>For a few weeks now I’ve been suffering from a terrible pain in my left side, tracing from about the middle of my left pec right round under the armpit. I remember first feeling it after the most recent charity roda in Edinburgh. I assumed it was an injury sustained <em>in</em> the roda but I couldn’t remember how exactly.</p>
<p>I left things a week, going so far as to stop doing handstands every night in order to give my side a rest. This proved incredibly difficult, and the next time I cracked and started doing handstands again the pain came back. The next morning I was in agony.</p>
<p>At the weekend in Drumnadrochit (which I’ll write about in another post) I tried to arm a berimbau and the pains in my side came back as hard as ever. At that point I realised that the real cause of my pain must have been trying to arm a particularly stiff viola (high-pitched berimbau), with what was clearly poor technique.</p>
<p>I need to practise stringing them using more body weight and less strength because that way, I hope, there will be fewer musical instrument-based injuries in future.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Wed, 15 May 2013 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2013-05-15-pain-in-all-the-diodes.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>A capoeira weekend in Drumnadrochit</title>
    <link>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2013-05-10-a-capoeira-weekend-in-drumnadrochit.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>I’m just getting ready for weekend up north with the <a href="http://maonochao.org/2013/05/06/evening-classes-and-workshop-with-cm-dion/" title="Workshop with Dion near Inverness">Mão no Chão people and Dion</a>. I’ve got some bread getting ready, the hallway is piled high with an unsorted collection of things I could take including a tent and sleeping bags. I’m trying to work out if it’s possible to book train tickets home that are not eye-wateringly expensive. (The answer would appear to be “no”.)</p>
<p>The weather in Drumnadrochit says “rain” so a tent will probably not be so fun. I suspect thick socks and shoes might actually be more prudent, though we don’t plan on going for long walks.</p>
<p>I also have to think about getting something for lunch! Right, better get back to that bread, it’ll need worked a bit more and there’s no time to lose.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Fri, 10 May 2013 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2013-05-10-a-capoeira-weekend-in-drumnadrochit.html</guid>
</item>

    </channel> 
</rss>
