<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>Looking Out To Sea</title>
        <link>http://dougalstanton.net</link>
        <description><![CDATA[A blog of sorts, unsorted.]]></description>
        <atom:link href="http://dougalstanton.net/rss.xml" rel="self"
                   type="application/rss+xml" />
        <lastBuildDate>Mon, 27 May 2013 00:00:00 UT</lastBuildDate>
        <item>
    <title>Star Trek Into Darkness a spectacle but nothing more</title>
    <link>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2013-05-27-star-trek-into-darkness-a-spectacle-but-nothing-more.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>We saw <em>Star Trek Into Darkness</em> last night, the second film since Hollywood decided to restart the series by showing us young Kirk, young Spock etc, before the events of the original television series. In fact, the film ends at the beginning of the “five year mission” that is part of the opening monologue for <em>Star Trek</em>.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/matthewsheean/3636722887/"
title="Star Trek Guys by Matthew Sheean, on Flickr"><img
src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3390/3636722887_713cbdf8f8.jpg"
width="323" height="500" alt="Star Trek Guys"
style="float:left;margin-right:10px;"></a></p>
<p>This film was disappointing for many insubstantial reasons. Much of the scenes were lifted from previous Star Trek — if you know your lore you’ll be guessing (correctly) how scenes unfold from the opening lines. So, heavy nods to the fans on this one, but for no particular reason.</p>
<p>Also, the bad guys in this were a bit underdeveloped. John Harrison, the spy played by Benedict Cumberbatch (Hollywood’s English-bad-guy <em>du jour</em>: move over Alan Rickman), is another nod to the fans<sup><a href="#fn1" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref1">1</a></sup> and a well-known character, though it’s getting to the point that some people have so many “origin stories” that they’re no longer discrete people. They are personality probability functions which depend on the observer to show something new at each moment. Some stories make full use of this — the Joker eventually made a career of lying about how he got his smile — but when everybody starts doing it the novelty quickly wears thin.</p>
<p>I was not angry at the story like I was angry coming away from <em>Prometheus</em> but they could certainly have made a more coherent tale. They spent so long in the last film bringing together the crew we know and love. This film made an inexpert attempt to drive a wedge between them but some of the premises were so hamfisted (the world’s weakest lovers’ tiff between Spock and Uhura) that I was bored of the attempts.</p>
<p>Who else has seen it? Any humble opinions?</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr />
<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>I’m trying not to give spoilers here so bear with me.<a href="#fnref1">↩</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Mon, 27 May 2013 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2013-05-27-star-trek-into-darkness-a-spectacle-but-nothing-more.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Capoeira workshop in Drumnadrochit</title>
    <link>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2013-05-27-capoeira-workshop-in-drumnadrochit.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>At the weekend I was up north with Helen and a number of other people from <em>Mão no Chão Capoeira Angola</em>. The <a href="http://www.diondragas.com" title="Dion&#39;s home page">group’s founder, Dion</a>, was over from Greece to take the weekend workshop.</p>
<p>We took a car up on Friday, leaving only two hours behind schedule (a record of punctuality where we are concerned). I had enough time to bake a loaf of bread to take, but not enough space in the car to pack a tent. We even had some of the half-done berimbaus from the instrument-making session strapped to the roof rack.</p>
<p>We drove to Inverness, gathered some supplies and then switched south again on the other side of Loch Ness to Drumnadrochit for pizza and chips before heading to Fraser’s house on the shore of Loch Meiklie. Helen got the train into Inverness and we picked her up later that evening.</p>
<p>We all slept on the floor of Fraser’s living room that night because it was too wet to think about putting the tent up. I didn’t find the sleeping bag and mat much of a problem and slept reasonably well. I think I was woken by a slobbery dog on at least one of the days — the perils of lying on the ground.</p>
<p>After a lazy breakfast we put some more work into the instruments we’d brought with us. Then it was a bit of lunch and down to Glenurquhart Public Hall in Drumnadrochit for the Saturday afternoon of training. In the evening Fraser’s wife brought down big pans full of curry and rice which we had in the hall, in the well-appointed kitchen attached. If you’re looking for a venue up that way I can really recommend it on facilities (I have no idea how much it cost).</p>
<p>I was still quite sore from my mysterious muscle injury in my side (see previous post) — I wouldn’t work out what it was until the Sunday — so I was taking things easy and not doing a lot of the inverted stuff or anything which required stretching my arms behind me. Which is unfortunate because there was a heavy emphasis on <a href="http://cs.i.uol.com.br/album/1108_capoeira_f_024.jpg" title="Ponte, that is, bridge">ponte</a> which is basically all about being inverted, stretching arms behind you and taking your weight on them.</p>
<p>After class and the meal Helen and I nipped round the village to get some air and stopped in at <a href="http://www.fiddledrum.co.uk/" title="Restaurant and more">Fiddlers</a> for a sly half pint — sitting in the beer garden in what was left of the sunshine.</p>
<p>In the evening we stayed up drinking and watching crazy videos on YouTube of handbalancing, Cyr wheels and people who jump off cliffs without a safety net.</p>
<p>After lunch the next day we went to Drumnadrochit with everyone else and while they settled in for the second session of the weekend we boarded the (expensive) bus to Inverness to catch our train to Edinburgh and see Paper Aeroplanes at the Voodoo Rooms (a very fine gig).</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Mon, 27 May 2013 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2013-05-27-capoeira-workshop-in-drumnadrochit.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Pain in all the diodes down my left side</title>
    <link>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2013-05-15-pain-in-all-the-diodes.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>For a few weeks now I’ve been suffering from a terrible pain in my left side, tracing from about the middle of my left pec right round under the armpit. I remember first feeling it after the most recent charity roda in Edinburgh. I assumed it was an injury sustained <em>in</em> the roda but I couldn’t remember how exactly.</p>
<p>I left things a week, going so far as to stop doing handstands every night in order to give my side a rest. This proved incredibly difficult, and the next time I cracked and started doing handstands again the pain came back. The next morning I was in agony.</p>
<p>At the weekend in Drumnadrochit (which I’ll write about in another post) I tried to arm a berimbau and the pains in my side came back as hard as ever. At that point I realised that the real cause of my pain must have been trying to arm a particularly stiff viola (high-pitched berimbau), with what was clearly poor technique.</p>
<p>I need to practise stringing them using more body weight and less strength because that way, I hope, there will be fewer musical instrument-based injuries in future.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Wed, 15 May 2013 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2013-05-15-pain-in-all-the-diodes.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>A capoeira weekend in Drumnadrochit</title>
    <link>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2013-05-10-a-capoeira-weekend-in-drumnadrochit.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>I’m just getting ready for weekend up north with the <a href="http://maonochao.org/2013/05/06/evening-classes-and-workshop-with-cm-dion/" title="Workshop with Dion near Inverness">Mão no Chão people and Dion</a>. I’ve got some bread getting ready, the hallway is piled high with an unsorted collection of things I could take including a tent and sleeping bags. I’m trying to work out if it’s possible to book train tickets home that are not eye-wateringly expensive. (The answer would appear to be “no”.)</p>
<p>The weather in Drumnadrochit says “rain” so a tent will probably not be so fun. I suspect thick socks and shoes might actually be more prudent, though we don’t plan on going for long walks.</p>
<p>I also have to think about getting something for lunch! Right, better get back to that bread, it’ll need worked a bit more and there’s no time to lose.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Fri, 10 May 2013 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2013-05-10-a-capoeira-weekend-in-drumnadrochit.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>A new home and new instruments</title>
    <link>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2013-04-29-a-new-home-and-new-instruments.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>The initial enthusiasm for finding a new venue has been slowly waning over the weeks as we chapped on more doors and got more unhelpful responses. For the few venues that didn’t just say no there were other problems — mostly cost.</p>
<p>To distract us from issues of training spaces we gathered on Saturday past to rebuild our stock of instruments. We lost three berimbaus in the fire at the Steiner school so the plan was to get some replacements for the Glasgow group. We finished about five or six verga, waxed and with fresh leather caps for the few that were being refurbished. We used the recently harvested wire for new arame on these. The last stage we’ve not done anything about yet — preparing gourds and eventually marrying up the cabaças to make completed berimbaus.</p>
<p>And today I’m just back from <a href="http://www.thespace-glasgow.com/" title="Studios for Performing Arts and Creative Enterprise">The SPACE</a>, which is approximately equivalent to the Out of the Blue drill hall in Leith, though less community-based. It’s in the floors above the Argyle Arcade so it’s harder to get at — the ground floor has many jewellery shops which don’t appreciate people tramping past at all hours.</p>
<p>It seems an interesting space which could provide something useful. The other option on the cards after a lot of hunting is the Overnewton Recreation Centre, curiously enough right next door to the Steiner school. For long enough they have not answer our calls but eventually we got through to them. The future of the space is under question but it seems we could get use of it for the next six months.</p>
<p>Finally things are looking up!</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Mon, 29 Apr 2013 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2013-04-29-a-new-home-and-new-instruments.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>The world discovers that programming is not easy</title>
    <link>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2013-04-21-the-world-discovers-that-programming-is-not-easy.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>It has recently been shown that <a href="http://www.guardian.co.uk/politics/2013/apr/18/uncovered-error-george-osborne-austerity" title="Erroneous Excel spreadsheet source for austerity measures">a 2010 economics paper built around an Excel spreadsheet contained an important error</a>, and this error came from the code in the spreadsheet itself. To be exact, some conclusions of the paper hinged on a spreadsheet bug.</p>
<p>So it becomes clear to the world at large that Excel spreadsheets are programming, and being programming they will almost definitely contain bugs.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>As soon as we started programming, we found to our surprise that it wasn’t as easy to get programs right as we had thought. Debugging had to be discovered. I can remember the exact instant when I realized that a large part of my life from then on was going to be spent in finding mistakes in my own programs.</p>
<p>— Maurice Wilkes discovers debugging, 1949</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I have a particular interest here because I believe that programming should be something more widely taught and understood. Part of this greater understanding and familiarity will of course hammer home a truth understood by programmers all over the world: it’s very easy to make a mistake which doesn’t show up until too late.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 21 Apr 2013 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2013-04-21-the-world-discovers-that-programming-is-not-easy.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Finally, proof I can read</title>
    <link>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2013-04-13-finally-proof-i-can-read.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>It’s been ages since I finished a book. I’m having real trouble sticking to it right now but I’m not sure why. I guess everything I pick up isn’t engaging me but that doesn’t answer the question why my current threshold for engagement is so high.</p>
<p>So I’m happy to state that I finished <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lost_at_Sea_(comics)" title="Lost at Sea, the graphic novel">Lost at Sea by Bryan Lee O’Malley</a>, who is also the author of the Scott Pilgrim series. (Which for the record I haven’t read or seen the film, I just found this fact interesting.) I enjoyed it greatly. It’s about a girl discovering some friends on an accidental road trip and deals with the important issues of the day — whether cats can steal your soul, that kind of thing.</p>
<p>And it’s a graphic novel/comic and short, which goes more than some way to explain why I managed to finish it. It probably only has about 20 pages worth of text, but the medium doesn’t require many words. It’s unlikely I can claim that each picture adds another thousand to the word count.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sat, 13 Apr 2013 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2013-04-13-finally-proof-i-can-read.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Comics from the halfbakery</title>
    <link>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2013-04-10-comics-from-the-halfbakery.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>I have finally got my act together and started writing some code and even uploaded it! Check out <a href="http://github.com/dougalstanton/comicbake">http://github.com/dougalstanton/comicbake</a> where you will find the latest copy of the long-dormant Comic Bake.</p>
<p>So what is Comic Bake? What was it back in the day? It’s a tool for converting little text files into comics. The files are designed to be as easy to write as possible, and are inspired by the likes of play scripts and Markdown documents.</p>
<p>The actual format is actually in a bit of flux at the moment as I recently decided what I was using wasn’t ideal and so I’ve cleaned things up. In fact last night was spent cleaning up the parser considerably, not least because the code was several years old and my understanding of parser combinators and such has moved on since then. I’ve had more practice!</p>
<p>The scripts are combined with standard images provided by the user<sup><a href="#fn1" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref1">1</a></sup> and the resulting comic strip, with text in bubbles and all that, written back out to disk. I’m always shocked that it works, to be honest!</p>
<p>At some point obviously I want to (a) put it on Hackage and maybe (b) look into binary releases so people don’t have to install the entirety of the Haskell Platform and various development libraries (ImageMagick <em>and</em> GD, talk about indecisive!) just to use it. It’s not quite at the initial release stage yet though. I want to make it a bit more usable and maybe improve the algorithm for speech bubble placement before I do that.</p>
<p>But I’m glad I pulled it out of the archive; I’m feeling really good about it now and finally getting to do some interesting coding after a long period of stagnation.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr />
<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>I realise as I write this that it would be a lot easier to use if there were “standard” images. Creating image maps so that Comic Bake knows where each character is has always been the least usable part of the experience. If I provide some defaults then what used to be the only way to do things now becomes “advanced” — there if you want it but not necessary.<a href="#fnref1">↩</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Wed, 10 Apr 2013 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2013-04-10-comics-from-the-halfbakery.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Looking to windward</title>
    <link>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2013-04-03-looking-to-windward.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>One of my absolute favourite authors, Iain (M) Banks, has announced he has late-stage cancer and is not expected to live out the year.</p>
<p>While he is making the most of his final months with family and friends the rest of the literary world is mourning him. This will no doubt come as a slight shock to him, but it isn’t surprising to me. He wrote some <em>exceedingly good books</em>.</p>
<p>Meanwhile the rest of us will maybe try to <a href="http://www.johnblackwriter.com/2012/10/04/poetic-licence-iain-m-banks-consider-phlebas-and-t-s-eliots-the-waste-land/" title="Iain M Banks and TS Eliot">grasp that wheel harder</a>.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Wed, 03 Apr 2013 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2013-04-03-looking-to-windward.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Glasgow capoeira is going to need a new training hall</title>
    <link>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2013-03-29-glasgow-capoeira-is-going-to-need-a-new-training-hall.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>You might have seen in the news that there was a fire at a school in Glasgow. What you might not have known was that this school was also where <a href="http://maonochao.org/2013/03/26/sad-news-for-glasgow/" title="Sad news for us!">Mao No Chao Glasgow</a> trained every Thursday evening at 6.30.</p>
<p>I’ve not been down to see the building, or at least what remains of it, but the fire was going basically all day so I suspect there isn’t much left but the stone exterior walls. And they’ll be too damaged for the building to be deemed sound I would guess.</p>
<p>As a group we have often spoken of trying to find new premises but it’s very easy not to put in effort or make decisions when you have something. This fire has forced our hand and we’ve already had serious discussions about a couple of venues nearby.</p>
<p>By next Thursday I hope I’ll be able to say “we have tried one new training area”, and maybe we’ll have tried out another not long after that. It would be great to end somewhere that gives us more visibility to fitness types (like a real gym) or that is in an easily accessible place.</p>
<p>Here’s to us, rising from the ashes!</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Fri, 29 Mar 2013 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2013-03-29-glasgow-capoeira-is-going-to-need-a-new-training-hall.html</guid>
</item>

    </channel> 
</rss>
