<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>Looking Out To Sea</title>
        <link>http://dougalstanton.net</link>
        <description><![CDATA[A blog of sorts, unsorted.]]></description>
        <atom:link href="http://dougalstanton.net/rss.xml" rel="self"
                   type="application/rss+xml" />
        <lastBuildDate>Sat, 09 Nov 2013 00:00:00 UT</lastBuildDate>
        <item>
    <title>That's not my bag baby (my bag's gone missing)</title>
    <link>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2013-11-09-thats-not-my-bag-baby.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>Yesterday on the way to work the train was really busy so I put my rucksack in the overhead storage space… and forgot about it. I remembered at the exact moment that the final carriage was moving past me as I stood on the platform at Linlithgow station.</p>
<p>I reported the loss at the desk in Linlithgow train station and they phoned ahead to Waverley where the train was to terminate. I left my details and they phoned later to say that nothing had been found.</p>
<p>I phoned Edinburgh Waverley and Glasgow Queen Street lost property offices several times over the day to see if anything had been handed in by a passenger but no such luck. Apart from the rucksack itself I’ve lost:</p>
<ul>
<li>A wallet with two bank cards, a driving licence, some stamps and ten pounds in cash; and a coin purse with about four quid in small change. There will be other stuff in the wallet that I’ve forgotten about that will come to light in future when I realise it’s not available.</li>
<li>A spare battery for my front light and an Allen key multitool to deal with any bikey problems that may arise on my journey.</li>
<li>A pair of waterproof trousers, borrowed from my mum a few years ago for attending Traquair Fair in the rain and never given back. Sorry!</li>
<li>Also a gel ink pen, two bananas and an apple. That was for my lunch!</li>
</ul>
<p>The wallet is a logistical pain because it leaves me without ready access to cash at a weekend when Helen is away. The loss of the battery is annoying because (i) I just bought those lights and (ii) I spent extra on the pack with the spare battery which I never got to use.</p>
<p>A day later and neither lost property office has anything which matches my description so I will have to resign myself to cancelling, renewing and repurchasing various things. I’ve already cancelled the bank cards but now I need to get a replacement driving licence and a new wallet to put everything in. The rucksack wasn’t a great purchase anyway so maybe it’s good that I can replace that with something better for our current needs.</p>
<p>The battery I can do without — it was a spare and they are readily rechargable. (It’s a <a href="http://www.cateye.com/uk/products/detail/HL-EL460RC/" title="300 lumen front light with swappable, USB rechargable battery">CatEye Volt300</a> if you’re interested. As well as being bright it is USB rechargable so I can plug it in at work.) The Allen keys will need replaced because the flat is rapidly filling up with bikes that need maintenance and adjustment. The tool had seven different sizes of key and we have used most of them!</p>
<p>Lack of waterproof trousers will be cold in the short term (I can cycle in shorts if it’s raining) but not something I want to sustain. I don’t have the kind of commute which allows me to get really warm from just pedalling when in the depths of winter.</p>
<p>The loss of the apple and bananas has left me inconsolable.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sat, 09 Nov 2013 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2013-11-09-thats-not-my-bag-baby.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Roda with Glasgow Senzala and Professor Ouriço</title>
    <link>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2013-11-09-roda-with-glasgow-senzala-and-professor-ourico.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>The Glasgow Senzala recently had an open roda and workshop with Professor Ourico<sup><a href="#fn1" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref1">1</a></sup>. I didn’t make it for the workshop but managed to get there for most of the roda.</p>
<p>I realise only now (about a week later?) that this was probably my first roda as a proper outsider. There was a workshop but I didn’t attend. The group was not an angola group. The leader of the roda was not an angoleiro. I think every roda I have attended in the past at least one of these things has been familiar to me but this time round everything was foreign.</p>
<p>At the time I felt very unsure how much I should “remain true” and how much I should try to compromise for the capoeira that was, to some degree, expected. The music was very fast — should I play fast all the time? That’s not really something I can sustain. I realised soon that it wasn’t something that other people could manage.</p>
<p>The “speed dating” approach to capoeira (as Simon described it, at least) left me unsure how interact. I felt rude buying into a game before it really got started; but then if I didn’t buy in somebody else would and then I’d never get to play. Once I’d cut in there was no chance for the game to warm up and develop; it was just straight in there full speed ahead all the time. And while there may be a time and a place for that I really missed the chance to play a decent length game. (Of course it re-emphasised what I feel is good about the slow development and slower games. I often struggle not to push things to the next level so this is a lesson I would do well to learn!)</p>
<p>I also felt unsure around so many people who seemed unsure themselves, or at least were obviously not experts. Was I being too harsh/aggressive? I’m not a very unpredictable player by any means but unfamiliarity makes everything seem twice as unpredictable — they didn’t know me and I didn’t know them. They moved differently so I had a harder time telling the relative levels of expertise.</p>
<p>It’s a tricky one but overall I would definitely like to go for more rodas there because they did things so differently.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr />
<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>This apparently means hedgehog!<a href="#fnref1">↩</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sat, 09 Nov 2013 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2013-11-09-roda-with-glasgow-senzala-and-professor-ourico.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Writing: from LaTeX to nae tech</title>
    <link>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2013-11-04-writing-from-latex-to-nae-tech.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>I’ve always been quite fond of <a href="http://www.latex-project.org" title="LaTeX: A document preparation system">LaTeX</a> as an environment for composing long text, particularly since you can use whichever text editor you prefer and aren’t tied to any particular user interface. The output is also pretty high quality.</p>
<p>The downsides can’t be ignored, however. The language itself is one of those tales which grew in the telling — the result being a Turing complete macro language which isn’t really designed as a programming language but nor is it a particularly friendly markup language.</p>
<p>Also since most people use the LaTeX system on top of TeX there’s a certain degree to which the two are confused. There is no clean layer of abstraction since you can mix the two freely (to confusing result, in many cases).</p>
<p>Lately I’ve been using LaTeX as a backend for final document production but composing all of the documents themselves in Markdown-formatted text files. The conversion from one to the other comes courtesy of <a href="http://johnmacfarlane.net/pandoc/" title="Markup format-conversion swiss-army knife">PanDoc</a>, which is frankly the greatest thing since jammy pieces.</p>
<p>I’ve just finished putting together a nice system for writing letters using the two, which <a href="https://github.com/dougalstanton/scripts" title="Repository of little scripts and tools">I’ve uploaded to GitHub</a> alongside some instructions. The basic idea is that you drop the three files in your <code>~/bin</code> and the private <code>.pandoc</code> directory. There are a couple of places you should configure to enter your own settings, such as your name and home address.</p>
<p>The result uses the LaTeX “letter” document class to create nice PDFs without you needing to remember how the LaTeX nonsense works. You just type in some basic paragraphs, maybe without formatting of any kind, and the two systems deal with everything for you.</p>
<p>An example:</p>
<pre class="markdown"><code>---
to-name: Santa
to-address: [Santa Claus, Santa&#39;s Grotto, The North Pole]
---

I know it&#39;s only February but I&#39;ve been
very good this year and would like to put
in my request early. It would be great if
you could fix those potholes on Leith Walk
because frankly they&#39;re beyond a joke.</code></pre>
<p>If you leave out the “to-name” field it uses “Dear Sir or Madam” and closes with “Yours faithfully” automatically. I suppose the next step would be to customise the greeting and closing so you could write less formal letters (“Yours sincerely” is about as friendly as it gets) but that’s not much of a priority. If you’re going to write something casual you can probably write it by hand!</p>
<p>I’ve done a quick test recreating some letters I wrote in the past. Hardly the most rigorous of testing regimes but the principle is proven I think and I’ll definitely be using it in future.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Mon, 04 Nov 2013 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2013-11-04-writing-from-latex-to-nae-tech.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>One job ends and another begins</title>
    <link>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2013-11-01-one-job-ends-and-another-begins.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>On the 1st of November I finish my job working at Honeywell Security Group and will be moving to Calnex Solutions. I don’t yet know what my new role will involve, only in the broadest of terms. Whatever comes up during discussions at interview is only ever the simplest explanation that fits the moment. The devil is in the details.</p>
<p>I will be commuting further (but faster, so the distance won’t make much difference). Eventually we hope to return to our home in Edinburgh, if Helen and I end up working on the east coast. I will still be travelling by bike and I hope the environment will be nicer!</p>
<p>I hope to keep in touch with some of the people at Honeywell and maybe see them over Christmas for a chat in the pub or similar.</p>
<p>But in the mean time I will have to get used to a new routine with the pain of settling into a new job, learning new things and so forth. Wish me luck.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2013 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2013-11-01-one-job-ends-and-another-begins.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Public speaking and presentation: post match analysis</title>
    <link>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2013-10-26-public-speaking-post-match-analysis.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>My recent <a href="/posts/2013-10-13-aaargh-public-speaking.html" title="Previous thoughts (anxiety) on public speaking">foray into the realm of public speaking</a> went really well. I presented what was initially going to be a 30 minute talk on functional programming, which in the end last for closer to 45 minutes.</p>
<p>During development the topic changed from Haskell to functional programming in general to, ultimately, code reuse. I used Haskell as an example language to show ways in which custom control-flow operations (from the basic <code>map</code> and <code>fold</code> to the more abstract <code>&gt;&gt;=</code>) lets you write less code with more consistent semantics and pave the way for parallelising code if necessary.</p>
<p>The <a href="http://github.com/dougalstanton/intro-to-fp/" title="Source for slides and notes">slides and notes are available on GitHub</a>. Both documents are written in Markdown. I used Pandoc with support for the Reveal.js presentation framework to create a slick set of slides. (I think the look of the slides came across really well, compared to the usual Powerpoint fare.)</p>
<p>I wrote most of the presentation in prose format to begin with so that I had my ideas fully formed. I think this really helped form a cohesive story. In the past I’ve gone straight from “half-baked idea” to “creating slides” and it has been really easy to become confused about what I should be saying at each stage. Coming up with an initial story meant that I really knew what I was trying to say and most of the time knew what slide was coming up next without peeking.</p>
<p>I am definitely more influenced by the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Takahashi_method" title="Minimal full-screen slides in the style of Masayoshi Takahashi">Takahashi</a> and Lessig schools of presentation authoring — really minimising the amount of stuff on screen. The other important thing is not to read what is on screen. I think this is where coming up with a narrative first was really helpful: the slides I produced in the end were illustrations of my words, rather than the words being descriptions of my illustrations.</p>
<p>Obviously the totally-minimalist presentation style isn’t appropriate if you want to show code, which often requires four or five lines of text. But it’s still much better than two columns of small text with bullet points and a graph all on screen at once.</p>
<p>One thing I did learn from the actual presentation on the day — apart from the need to assume technical difficulties with the projector — is that the colour and detail you get projected onto the wall (even in a dark room) is much worse than the slides on your screen. I did a test run with the television at home but that still didn’t give me a proper idea how bad the final display would be. Err on the side of thicker lines and greater contrast between colours. I had one tree diagram illustrating an inverted tree. The branches of the tree were just black lines and became totally invisible when projected despite looking fine on my screen and on our television.</p>
<p>The total experience for me was a lot more relaxed than I was expecting. Whether this was due to good preparation, confidence in my knowledge of the subject, more self-confidence or other things that I can’t pinpoint right now, we’ll never know. I felt really in control and for the rest of the day was on a total high.</p>
<p>The feedback on the presentation was also very positive — that it ran at a measured pace, I didn’t seem flustered or get myself confused, I didn’t try to say five things at once and so on. In general people seemed to believe that I was in control, which in this instance I really felt I was. A miracle.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sat, 26 Oct 2013 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2013-10-26-public-speaking-post-match-analysis.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Aaargh! Public speaking</title>
    <link>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2013-10-13-aaargh-public-speaking.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>Recently there have been a few presentations at work, including one on the two languages <a href="http://www.python.org" title="The Python Programming Language">Python</a> and <a href="http://www.lua.org" title="The Lua Programming Language">Lua</a>. These are both <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Type_system" title="Type systems">dynamically typed languages</a> and as you might know I’m a static typing kinda guy. It seemed reasonable to take this opportunity to get some public speaking practice while providing a counterpoint to this recent languages talk.</p>
<p>The language we use at work is C++ with a bit of legacy C and some assembly in the darker corners. This is a wee bit object-oriented and very imperative — a whole world away from the Haskell that I would more than likely use as my example language.</p>
<p>(Other topics suggested by my colleagues were capoeira and software engineering in an independent Scotland. I’m trying to work out how I can make a few “functional programming in an independent Scotland” jokes but there’s nothing forthcoming. The obvious “separation of Church and state” joke isn’t relevant here!)</p>
<p>The issues which I <em>could</em> discuss are numerous, and there’s plenty of things I’d like to talk about that are not introductory. So sticking to the basics, I have some themes and topics:</p>
<ul>
<li>Functions, procedures, side-effects. Some definitions.</li>
<li>Purity &amp; referential transparency. Haskell is a language of extremes (the “hair shirt”) so we may as well discuss the advantages of this full-on expression-based approach to programming.</li>
<li>The benefits of an expressive type system. Not an FP-specific thing but it gives an opportunity to show one of Haskell’s strengths.</li>
<li>Laziness and the duality of data structures and control structures. Might be a bit mind-bending but nobody said it was going to be easy.</li>
<li>History of Turing machines and Lambda calculus. Not sure if it can be worked in without sounding too much like a lecture but it would help to push the idea that this is a fundamentally different approach to the problem of programming but at the same time it is just as powerful.</li>
</ul>
<p>I think I just need to start writing and see what I can come up with. Rearrange, edit, and so on — until I’m done.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 13 Oct 2013 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2013-10-13-aaargh-public-speaking.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Thoughts on Aliveness in Capoeira</title>
    <link>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2013-09-29-thoughts-on-aliveness-in-capoeira.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>There doesn’t seem to be much written on this topic online — at least not in English. I recommend you read <a href="http://www.straightblastgym.com/aliveness101.html" title="Aliveness 101 by Matt Thornton">Matt Thornton’s extended essay on the topic</a> for the full analysis of “aliveness” in training — he’s one of those writers who would rather write ten thousand words than stop after 1000 but ultimately it’s a worthwhile read. I enjoyed it anyway, and it plays to my prejudices about scepticism and empiricism.</p>
<p>The summary is obvious and boring when written like this: you must train under the circumstances you want to perform because in high pressure situations it will all fall apart.</p>
<p>The idea was formalised for martial arts training. If you don’t train against opponents who are resisting you every step of the way then you’ll never really know how you’ll react “in real life”, whether that’s in the ring or not. Martial arts which don’t emphasise working against other people don’t produce competent fighters.</p>
<p>The three elements identified by Matt Thornton’s definition are <em>movement</em>, <em>timing</em> and <em>energy</em>. Each of these elements can be trained without spontaneity (even with a partner) and this is a less “real” training scenario. At one end of the scale the movement is prescribed, the timing is stop/start and the energy enough to move but no more. At the other end of the scale the movement is unpredictable, the timing fast and the energy continuous.</p>
<p>I think it’s clear how at one end of the scale is a slow-motion demonstration and the other end is an unscripted fight. The idea of “aliveness” is that training should be performed as near to the second end of the scale as possible at all times while still remaining safe for the practitioners. Matt Thornton also suggests quickly scaling up to the point where that initial static demonstration becomes a spontaneous clash.</p>
<p>What does this have to do with capoeira? How “alive” is capoeira training? It seems that “aliveness” is often mistaken for “effectiveness” or other less-measurable statement — probably because, in the field it was conceived to explain, “aliveness” inferred “effectiveness”. Martial arts which train with resistive opponents (judo, BJJ, boxing, Muay Thai and so on) are also the ones with the best reputations for sporting success in mixed martial art competitions.</p>
<p>But in the training for judo, they train for judo matches. In training for boxing, they train for boxing matches. Certain situations are ignored. (If you want proof, have a look for some MMA matches between pure boxers and kickboxers. The shock when the boxer <em>really</em> realises there’s another game going on beneath waist height makes it all the more emotional to watch.) The adaptability to other circumstances is a lucky combination of good training and effective moves. That’s not why people train with “aliveness”.</p>
<p>I am not going to talk much about the “street effectiveness” of capoeira. I think it’s a silly topic with too many unstated assumptions that need pinned down first. But I do think that the idea of “training with aliveness” has direct applications to capoeira <em>as it is played</em>. I mean training capoeira to play in a roda. This is a much easier topic to discuss and doesn’t put capoeira on a different footing from judo or boxing. The only difference is the “ruleset”, which in capoeira is often obscure, unwritten and idiosyncratic.</p>
<p>The ideas of spontaneous movement, erratic timing and unpredictable energy are almost defining features of capoeira. Training for a roda should require lots of this and I think in most cases it does. But the roda can be a strange place where predictability is courted anyway — set pieces and chamadas exist and are used with some degree of frequency. Sometimes they’re used as they are learnt and often they are used as traps — shared jokes in which the setter of the trap and the person entering both know what can happen and want to test themselves against the conventions. The difference between a straight run and a trap is of course impossible to tell under afterwards.</p>
<p>There is also a lot to learn about capoeira outside of the martial movements of the roda. Singing, music and ritual are as important to it all and they require a great deal of co-ordination and co-operation. Not everything you learn in class can be against resisting partners!</p>
<p>The only downside I can really see (apart from maybe a de-emphasis of the playfulness?) is that it’s really hard work. But that’s not surprising — the very act of their resistance requires work to overcome what your partner wants to do. It demands greater fitness and greater mental effort. But both of these aspects force the body into getting better in themselves.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 29 Sep 2013 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2013-09-29-thoughts-on-aliveness-in-capoeira.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Mestre Marrom workshop in London</title>
    <link>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2013-09-26-marrom-workshop-in-london.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.marromealunos.com" title="Marrom e Alunos">Mestre Marrom</a> was in north London doing a capoeira workshop at the weekend (20–22 September 2013). Various people from Mao No Chao went down from Scotland. I took the sleeper bus down on the Friday night with a handful of others and we arrived in London at 7am. Luckily we had planned for this and made enquiries of the best greasy spoon to get breakfast near to the workshop venue. Somewhere called Crystal Cafe in Homerton, I think.</p>
<p>I’d never met Marrom so this was a first. There were a lot of people from many London groups and further afield too. The hall was slightly too small for the number of people. When we were working in lines it was easy for the people at the edges of the rooms to run out of space when travelling sideways or backwards. It also made seeing across the crowd of people difficult.</p>
<p>We did some bits of pair work, and some sequences down the hall singly and in pairs. Then a double roda with a single bateria and at the end of each day a full roda. A number of local mestres came in for this — it was good to see them play — Fantasma, Axe, Joaozinho, Polaco and probably others who I forget. It was great to see all the different styles of play. (There are <a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UC0XIpNi5iwFCIXh56u2rSpA" title="Urban Ritual channel with videos from the workshop">some videos appearing on YouTube</a> being posted on the Urban Ritual channel.)</p>
<p>Overall I felt totally out of place being there. The level of skill was so far out of reach for me that I was just getting in the way. I basically spent the whole weekend uncomfortable and anxious without really taking anything in.</p>
<p>Marrom’s capoeira is very direct and grounded. It doesn’t give much away. Apart from ground — I often thought he escaped a long way out of an attack, often to re-enter very quickly with a hard attack. But quick chapas were something of a theme, both of his style and the weekend.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Thu, 26 Sep 2013 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2013-09-26-marrom-workshop-in-london.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>The game is a reflection of the players</title>
    <link>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2013-09-09-the-game-is-a-reflection-of-the-players.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>I enter the roda wanting to play elegantly and beautifully — wanting to be in control of myself. If the other person is playing at a level where I don’t feel threatened then I can concentrate on myself, and how the interaction feels. But when the pressure is turned up I concentrate on being in control of the other person. If the other person is playing above my level and I feel threatened then the urge to “fight back” starts to dominate. I start to lose what little control I had over myself in a futile attempt at mastery over the situation.</p>
<p>This has wider implications than just my growth as a capoeirista. The immediate requirements — to try twice as hard to play really well and be in control of myself, and let everything else fall out as it may — are fairly clear. Being more comfortable with my shortcomings and all that.</p>
<p>But there is more than that. This is the roda as a microcosm for life and social interaction. This illustrates how I react when I’m out of my depth. I would rather fake it than be honest about my shortcomings: in the roda I will be slapdash and uncontrolled rather than controlled but underwhelming; in life I would rather remain silent and appear competent than ask questions. I would rather appear angry than incompetent.</p>
<hr />
<p>A common interview question is to ask about weaknesses. What the real intention behind this question is nobody knows any more. Some people recommend trying to spin a positive to seem like a bad thing (“oh I’m too hard working”) while others say this is too obvious and you should be honest but show how you mitigate this. I suppose we can all agree that admitting to kleptomania or torturing kittens will probably not go in your favour.</p>
<p>What nobody talks about is that spotting your own flaws can be really incredibly difficult. They are hard to spot and harder to admit to yourself as real problems. Just writing the above passages is quite painful, even though in hindsight <em>I always knew this to be true</em>. I can think of countless scenarios where they apply.</p>
<p>I don’t know what I will do in the future with this extra level of self-knowledge.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Mon, 09 Sep 2013 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2013-09-09-the-game-is-a-reflection-of-the-players.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>A new yeast project: brewing</title>
    <link>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2013-08-23-a-new-yeast-project-brewing.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>Since moving to Glasgow we’ve been lumbered with a terrible oven which doesn’t get hot enough to really do justice to bread baking. Instead I decided to go different avenue and try some home brewing. It’s yeast Jim, but not as we know it.</p>
<p>I bought a fermenting bucket, a plastic tube, hydrometer, thermometer and airlock from the good people at <a href="http://www.innhousebrewery.co.uk/" title="Innhouse Brewery Company">Glasgow’s eminent homebrew shop</a>. Alongside that I bought the ingredients for a Canadian lager. A friend at work donated some used beer bottles and the use of his crown capper.</p>
<p>My two obstacles were cleanliness and temperature. Getting and keeping everything sterilised is a hard task. You can never tell until the ferment has worked whether you succeeded in cleaning everything properly. I started the ferment right in the middle of an uncommonly hot few weeks, so finding a dark cool part of the house was a challenge.</p>
<p>The actual steps to take were very simple and there are a wide variety of videos online that you can watch to provide extra clues. When siphoning and bottling it would have been useful to have an extra pair of hands (or more sophisticated tools) but I muddled through.</p>
<p>At the stage of writing the beer has been bottled for five days. It will stay in the bottle for another two weeks to “condition”, which should add some carbonation and let the flavour mature and settle a bit. I am looking forward to seeing how it all turns out. Will it be drinkable?</p>
<hr />
<p>It’s been conditioning in the bottle for two weeks now and I opened one this evening to see how it was progressing. The taste was mildly hoppy but slightly “thin” somehow. There wasn’t as much carbonation as I’d hoped. I think I may have put too little sugar in the bottles before capping them. But still pretty drinkable, and should be better again in a week’s time.</p>
<hr />
<p>Taste number two, about five days later, and things seemed much better — either because I had lower expectations or because more time means better flavour. I’m happy to let others taste it now.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Fri, 23 Aug 2013 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2013-08-23-a-new-yeast-project-brewing.html</guid>
</item>

    </channel> 
</rss>
