<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>Looking Out To Sea</title>
        <link>http://dougalstanton.net</link>
        <description><![CDATA[A blog of sorts, unsorted.]]></description>
        <atom:link href="http://dougalstanton.net/rss.xml" rel="self"
                   type="application/rss+xml" />
        <lastBuildDate>Sun, 21 Jun 2015 00:00:00 UT</lastBuildDate>
        <item>
    <title>Body painting for fun and (educational) profit</title>
    <link>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2015-06-21-body-painting-for-fun-and-educational-profit.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/universityofedinburgh/17797386523" title="Art and anatomy event illustrates the wonders of the human body by The University of Edinburgh, on Flickr"><img src="https://c4.staticflickr.com/8/7737/17797386523_e1b8559b3f.jpg" width="500" height="333" alt="Art and anatomy event illustrates the wonders of the human body"></a></p>
<p><a href="https://www.facebook.com/artandanatomyedinburgh" title="Art and Anatomy Facebook page">Art and Anatomy</a> is a group which aims to teach anatomy to medical students at Edinburgh university through artistic methods: body painting and sculpture being the two obvious approaches. As a promotional thing they ran an evening session for the public, letting people have a go at sculpting clay hearts and painting the structures of the hand onto each other.</p>
<p>At the same time American artist <a href="https://www.facebook.com/pages/Danny-Quirk-Artwork/283073600976" title="Danny Quirk&#39;s Facebook page">Danny Quirk</a> was nearby (well, London) for a seminar so agreed to come to Edinburgh and demonstrate his own body painting techniques. He has done a lot of anatomical painting on bodies. His images use acrylic paint and marker pen rather than “face paint” which is water based, so his body paintings are so much more vivid and powerful.</p>
<p>Helen had agreed to help out with some of the anatomical teaching side of the day and as soon as I saw photos of Danny Quirk’s work I knew I wanted to volunteer. As luck would have it the model that had been arranged (another medic) had a latex allergy — and the acrylic/marker pen is painted onto a transparent latex layer which is directly on the skin. Clearly she was not the best candidate so I stepped up to the mark.</p>
<p>We started early — I stripped off my shirt and painting began before 8 AM. We took a brief few minutes out for lunch and a few toilet breaks but basically the work continued until about four o’clock in the afternoon. Walking through the halls of the medical school building topless to visit the toilet was quite amusing. I’m unsure how many people who saw me knew what was happening; it wasn’t obvious I was painted until I was walking away.</p>
<p>The evening lecture was the point at which Danny unveiled his new work (ie me). Then the audience went off to their chosen workshops and to look round the medical artifacts museum and the “artist’s studio” where medical illustrators in the past would work from the results from the dissection table.</p>
<p>The day received a lot of press and there were photographers in from the university and a bunch of high profile papers/press agencies. My photo appeared in the Metro and the BMJ while others got into the Herald etc. You can see the <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/universityofedinburgh/sets/72157653536069500" title="Edinburgh University photos from Art &amp; Anatomy event">university press’s official photographs here</a>.</p>
<p>The latex sheet was removed in one piece the following day and you can see the video of the process. The whole thing took nearly an hour but it’s been edited so you don’t lose all interest. I don’t have a hairy back but removing a full sheet of latex wasn’t a pleasant experience. The tiny hairs near the spine seemed to be a consistent source of pain. I would recommend anyone who did this in future to just shave regardless of how unhairy you are.</p>
<iframe class="show" width="420" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/xvsgNR7aR9I?rel=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>

<p>We’ve still got the piece at the moment, weighted down on a piece of mounting board under plastic sheet and heavy (anatomy) textbooks. The plan is to get some kind of boxes to display it like items in a specimen case. Meanwhile Danny’s promised to send a cleaned up photograph of me and my back to keep on the wall.</p>
<p>Totally great, really glad I signed up for the day.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jun 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2015-06-21-body-painting-for-fun-and-educational-profit.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Cycling and camping at Knockengorroch festival</title>
    <link>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2015-06-01-cycling-and-camping-at-knockengorroch-festival.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>It all went according to plan. I took the train from Edinburgh to Glasgow Queen Street station, talking to a guy who was cycling up the west coast for a week. We discussed riding on the continent, the value of step-through frames when you get old enough that stepping over the saddle is difficult, and the easy nature of Rohloff internal hub gears.</p>
<p>From Queen Street I rode round the corner to Central Station and boarded the train to Ayr. I spoke to a woman wearing civvies but riding a skinny road bike. She had cleated cycling shoes to provide the interface: more roadie than casual on the feet. She soon realised she was on the wrong train and got off at the next station to return on the next available train.</p>
<p>I arrived at Ayr and found a Greggs to sell me two sausage rolls and a fudge donut for lunch. They were sold out of fudge donuts so I had to make do with chocolate, which I call “slumming it”. I set off straight away following the Bike Hub app which is absolutely terrible. The on-screen map isn’t very detailed. Your location on the map is marked with a small circle which means your own direction isn’t obvious. The map also doesn’t re-orient as you turn, so it quickly becomes useless at junctions — peering at the tiny writing for road names and hunting around for the related street signs makes for very frustrating progress. I switched to Google Maps before I left Ayr.</p>
<p>The A713 is a straightforward but unpleasant road from Ayr to Carlisle through the town of Dalmellington. The festival is a few miles beyond Dalmellington so I was mostly following the road signs. I stopped in a layby while the traffic got busy to eat my sausage rolls. I passed a few lone cyclists and a couple on a touring tandem. I was tempted by the Hollybush Inn at the top of a hill but it was still early in the day. I kept going.</p>
<p>I stopped later near the Scottish steam engine centre (or something) for my chocolate donut. The chocolate was quite runny but not bad. I didn’t visit the steam trains. I had set off behind schedule and wasted a lot of time trying to get out of Ayr so I had little time to waste on sightseeing.</p>
<p>I went up some narrow, winding roads between Dalmellington and the turn-off to the festival site. Most of the traffic at this point was quite good with the occasional scary idiot. Seeing police cordon tape and bits of wrecked cars (including the whole front bumper and registration number of a blue car) that had been flung ten metres off the road in some high-speed collision was quite sobering and more than a little alarming. It’s easy to feel very vulnerable in such a situation — because truly you are vulnerable.</p>
<p>I reach the turn-off for Knockengorroch which was about half a mile of uphill followed by three miles of downhill. Exhilerating when you’ve been slogging for so long! I think I arrived at the area of grass that would be my pitch at about 5.30. It was getting colder so I’m glad I didn’t waste any time.</p>
<hr />
<p>The festival went reasonably well though I suffered from poor wardrobe choice a lot of the time. Warmer clothes, including a better jacket, would have really cheered me up. On my last night I ended up wearing most of my cycling gear underneath my day clothes because it was so chilly.</p>
<hr />
<p>On the return journey I left just before noon, forcing my way up the long downhill to the festival site and back onto the main road. My initial impression that the route had been quite uphill on the way seemed accurate: it was a lot more downhill on the return journey with some spots that were considerably faster to travel than my average. I think about 8mph had been my pace on the way out. I stopped for my lunch at the aforementioned Hollybush Inn on the way back but I would have made much better time otherwise.</p>
<p>In future I would try to travel by more obscure routes if possible, leaving more time where necessary. I would have better paper maps and a better plan to escape the big cities (well, escape Ayr). Ending up on dual carriageways and motorways is all too easy: nobody bothers signposting the slow roads with big signs!</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jun 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2015-06-01-cycling-and-camping-at-knockengorroch-festival.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Taking the bike to Knockengorroch, what an idea!</title>
    <link>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2015-05-19-taking-the-bike-to-knockengorroch.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>In a few short days I’m going to make my way to <a href="http://www.knockengorroch.org.uk" title="Knockengorroch festival, 21-24 May">Knockengorroch World Ceilidh 2015</a> by bike. I’ve taken Thursday, Friday and Monday off work to reduce the anxiety of the journey but I’ve still managed to convince myself that I’m not up to the challenge and reduced my journey further.</p>
<p>I had originally wanted to cycle there in two stages and to camp somewhere in between on the Thursday night. But now I’ve just decided to take the train to Ayr and travel the remainder of the distance by bike in one day — which is only 22 miles. This is the distance between work and home which I’ve done several times now and though I will be doing it laden with camping gear I will also have many hours to spare. Google Maps reckons I can do it in two and a half hours. Maybe it’ll be 3 hours in the end as Google doesn’t really know about hills or luggage.</p>
<p>I’ve had a trial run with panniers and tent loaded on the bike. I went for a sedate few miles on the NEPN in the Leith end of town. Tonight I will try to pack everything properly to work out what I need and where it should go.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Tue, 19 May 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2015-05-19-taking-the-bike-to-knockengorroch.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Reflections on using the arms in capoeira</title>
    <link>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2015-05-10-reflections-on-arm-use-in-capoeira.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>Since starting BJJ it’s been harder to remain disconnected from people when playing capoeira. Either I can fight this or embrace it and see where it leads. So what does it mean to be all “touchy touchy” in capoeira? Can I make something positive out of this?</p>
<p>Against a <em>meia lua</em> or <em>rabo de arraia</em> it makes sense to have contact with the kicking leg while moving out of the way. In particular slower kicks which can be easily reversed to kick from different directions. Ducking under a meia lua puts the face quite close to the kicking leg and it’s not uncommon for the person to shift their weight and come back with the foot right towards your face.</p>
<p>The traditional defence is a somewhat ambiguous “arms held out in midair” behaviour which means the hands are at the right height to prevent incoming strikes but are not very strong.</p>
<p>I wonder whether a better approach is a pre-emptive touch or “frame” to maintain the right distance and a sense of safety. Depending on the game it could be a back-of-the-hand, a bladed hand, a forearm or upper arm. The key difference between this and the normal defence is that the “acceleration” time of a strike is zero. The strength of the kick comes from the momentum when it strikes — if there is no distance before impact then the kick becomes a push and <em>meia lua</em> and <em>rabo de arraia</em> are not push kicks and have no strength like that.</p>
<p>Another detail of course is a tactical one. If you’ve got a hand on a person’s limb then you don’t need to watch it to know where it is and what direction it’s moving. You can spare your eyes for other places.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 10 May 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2015-05-10-reflections-on-arm-use-in-capoeira.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Lower gear on Fuji for Edinburgh's hills</title>
    <link>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2015-05-03-lower-gear-on-the-fuji-for-edinburghs-hills.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>The stock Fuji Track Classic comes with a 46/16 gear ratio, which works out at <a href="http://www.bikecalc.com/gear_inches">about 76 gear inches</a>. This is pretty good on a flat road. Riding across the work car park or along George Street is very relaxing. What it’s not great for is Edinburgh’s sharp inclines, particularly without a head start. Getting the initial forward movement on the hill in such a high gear is pretty harsh!</p>
<p>The solution then was to adjust the gear to something a bit lower. Replacing the 16 tooth cog with an 18T produces 67 inches which is a substantial step down. There’s always a trade off in these things and there were two here. The first of course is that a gear which is good for climbing is not good for descending. I must learn to spin faster (though this is always true). The second consideration is chain length since altering the cog size shifts everything around. The move to 18T is the most I can manage with this chain; anything larger would require an extra link in the chain to compensate.</p>
<p>Finally in the process of putting it all together I learned the difference between a fixed hub and a freewheel hub since my bike has one of each. On the fixed side there’s a slightly larger diameter forward-thread to accept the cog and then a smaller diameter section which is reverse threaded. The cog screws in “forward” and the lockring screws in “backward” to prevent the cog coming undone with a hard backpressure.</p>
<p>The other side has only a forward-threaded section: there is no room for a lockring. Opinions differ as to whether this is a bad thing or not. If the cog is wound tightly enough then it shouldn’t be, and each pedal stroke under normal use will tighten the cog further. Personally I would prefer the safety of a lockring and I would have put my new 18T cog on the side which fits the lockring… except I couldn’t get the old 16T off first! It’s had a lot of hard pushing and is quite firmly locked in place.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 03 May 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2015-05-03-lower-gear-on-the-fuji-for-edinburghs-hills.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Char is (probably) not short for Character</title>
    <link>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2015-05-02-char-is-not-short-for-character.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>I was reading an online discussion recently about the pronunciation of “char” as it appears in C source code. For the non-programmers, the keyword “char” is used to indicate a character (eg, letter or number) in code, like this:</p>
<pre class="sourceCode c"><code class="sourceCode c"><span class="dt">char</span> my_initial = &#39;D&#39;;</code></pre>
<p>Some people pronounce this keyword as it appears, <em>char</em> (as in to blacken by burning). Others pronounce it more like <em>car</em> with a hard /k/ since it’s short for <em>character</em>. But it occured to me that the vowel sound in <em>car</em> and in <em>character</em> are different — at least they are in my accent!</p>
<p>I looked them up and they appear different in IPA rendering too: /ɑ/ in <em>car</em> and /a/ in <em>character</em>.</p>
<p>I’m personally fond of pronouncing it like <em>char</em>, but if I wanted to go with the alternative could I learn to pronounce <em>car</em> with a different vowel sound? How weird would I sound?</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sat, 02 May 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2015-05-02-char-is-not-short-for-character.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Dwelling on a capoeira lesson plan</title>
    <link>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2015-04-15-dwelling-on-a-capoeira-lesson-plan.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>The other night I was kept from sleep by a cold and spent too much brainpower thinking and rethinking how to teach capoeira classes better. I could not sleep and I thought and because I was thinking it took much longer to reach sleep. But at least I had some fruitful thoughts.</p>
<p>The next day I was supposed to help teach a class because the main teachers were away. So while I worried at the problem and failed to get the sleep I needed, daybreak was getting closer and I was getting myself more sick. In the end I was too ill to take the class and it was basically aborted.</p>
<p>So the irony is apparent. I spent so long worrying about doing the class right that I couldn’t do it at all. Would it have been better to take the class under-prepared but less ill, or save the ideas for a future date? I think I made the right choice. I certainly feel like I made the right choice after a long sleep the following night — getting to bed early instead of teaching a class until late was definitely refreshing.</p>
<p>I was particularly worried about beginners to the class, because they’re the people who have the smallest amount of patience for a bad class. The regulars would forgive me if it didn’t all go right and they would return anyway. A beginner is more likely to take one look and walk away if they don’t like it.</p>
<p>Now that I am feeling healthier and less miserable I believe it would have been an okay class after all. At least for a first attempt.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Wed, 15 Apr 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2015-04-15-dwelling-on-a-capoeira-lesson-plan.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Sports as idle pastimes</title>
    <link>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2015-04-09-sports-as-idle-pastimes.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>We recently spent some holiday time in France with Kirsten, Oliver and other friends in their house. A whole week away from my usual physical routines of cycling, capoeira and grappling. We did a bit of casual cycling in Paris with a tour guide but it was strictly low-speed sight-seeing rather than exercise.</p>
<p>Some of the others in the house went out running and for the first time I was jealous of running. I’m never jealous of running because I don’t enjoy it but this time I wanted the activity, I wanted the camaraderie and I wanted the accessibility of it all.</p>
<p>Cycling can be done solo; some may say it’s best done solo though sharing a view at the top of a hill or a pint at the bottom is surely better than doing the same alone. Grappling obviously requires a (willing?) partner and a bit of soft ground though not necessarily much else. But if you suggest to most people whether they want to have a friendly wrestling match they would probably think you’re cracked.</p>
<p>Finally there’s capoeira, a pastime that has even been called <em>vadiação</em>, bumming around. But if you don’t have a bateria and a group of friends and so on you’ll still need another person who wants to play. That’s probably less likely than finding someone who wants to wrestle with you because most people who grew up with a sibling have at least wrestled before. <em>Nobody</em> knows what capoeira is all about. Bumming around is harder than it seems.</p>
<p>This is why I am jealous of running. A solo sport that you can do in groups and doesn’t need more equipment than what you’re standing in.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Thu, 09 Apr 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2015-04-09-sports-as-idle-pastimes.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Bike fit at Bike Craft (part 2)</title>
    <link>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2015-04-08-bike-fit-at-bike-craft-part-2.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>It’s been a month since my bike fit and re-adjustment at Bike Craft. Their loaned seat-post was swapped for a shiny new one<a href="#fn1" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref1"><sup>1</sup></a> and I’m slowly getting accustomed to the riding position.</p>
<p>I have not gone for any very long rides — nothing longer than my usual trips from Haymarket station or BJJ class. There is still the slightest hint of pain when I push the limits for an extended period but this is what I’d expect. Under normal circumstances I think that <em>should</em> happen: if it doesn’t hurt when you’re going flat out then are you really going flat out?</p>
<p>I can’t remember if I mentioned that the fixed gear bike seems to be set up more like the new configuration of the geared bike than the old configuration. This may explain the lack of pain riding that bike but since the toe traps don’t have any straps to lock my feet laterally onto the pedals I can’t really confirm anything. Maybe if my feet were held in place they would hurt just as much.</p>
<p>It sounds like Helen’s bike might also be a poor fit for her — a poor fit geometrically but also a poor fit for her requirements. I think we’re both coming to the conclusion that a touring/relaxed road bike is most suitable for our needs as an all-purpose machine. That’s certainly what I’d thought would be my next move.</p>
<p>In future I would be hesitant to buy a new bike without a proper bike fit, especially since most places will offset some or all of the cost of the fit against the bike anyway. Why pay money without that assurance?</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr />
<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Should it be possible to be impressed by a seat post? Is this healthy?<a href="#fnref1">↩</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Wed, 08 Apr 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2015-04-08-bike-fit-at-bike-craft-part-2.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Bike fit at Bike Craft (part 1)</title>
    <link>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2015-03-11-bike-fit-at-bike-craft-part-1.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>Since I got my first bike as an adult several years ago I noticed that I pedal with my feet on the outside of the pedals, splayed slightly outwards. This wasn’t a particular problem with flat pedals but if I am using toe clips or straps my legs felt uncomfortable and twisted. After a day of cycling I got pain behind my knee, particularly at the back of my right leg.</p>
<p>Doing the research pointed up an issue of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Q_factor_%28bicycles%29" title="Q factor for bicycles">“Q factor”</a>, the distance between the two planes in which the pedals move. Different bike designs (mountain, road, leisure) will differ due to bottom bracket size, the splay of the cranks and so on. But the racier the bike the narrower the distance between your feet.</p>
<p>Reasoning that my natural/desired Q factor was wider than one afforded by the design of my bike, I bought some <a href="http://www.specialized.com/gb/gb/ftb/mtb-components/pedals/body-geometry-pedal-axle-extenders" title="Pedal extenders (larger than life)">pedal extenders</a> — metal cylinders with a pedal-style male thread at one end and a crank-style female thread at the other. This seemed to solve the issue: my foot could be strapped in and I could pedal pedal pedal for hours without pain.</p>
<p>So where is this going? It’s going the way of all hacks, all “self-medication”. The niggling belief that there was something fundamentally wrong with my setup that I was not fixing but shifting elsewhere with the pedal extenders. With every new bike I buy, or every new saddle, or pedals, do I have to go through these experiments?</p>
<p>I arranged a fitting at <a href="http://bikecraftedinburgh.co.uk/" title="Bike Craft, Edinburgh">Bike Craft on Ferry Road</a>. They asked me about my cycling habits and distances, and the all important list of problems and aches I get. Then they set me up on a massage table to measure the flexibility of my hips. I knew this would be pretty terrible; despite the BJJ and capoeira I am still a stiff old board.</p>
<p>With all this data gathered I sat on my own bike on a trainer and made some adjustments, making sure to take before and after measurements. The seatpost was replaced with another that had a smaller offset — since my saddle was at its furthest forward to counteract the existing post’s large rearward offset. The saddle height was reduced. And the pedal extenders were removed.</p>
<p>I’ve got the temporary seatpost on loan for a few days to see how it works with the new height and without the pedal extenders. After all of the adjustments of the evening, and the unfamiliarity of my new riding position, I was unable to definitely say if it was better or worse than my usual position.</p>
<p>Initial impressions are that I feel more “inside” the bike. It feels more likely that I could get a higher cadence in this position, which does hint that I was too far away from the pedals before. I’ll give it a few days and a few more miles to see what happens.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Wed, 11 Mar 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2015-03-11-bike-fit-at-bike-craft-part-1.html</guid>
</item>

    </channel> 
</rss>
