<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>Looking Out To Sea</title>
        <link>http://dougalstanton.net</link>
        <description><![CDATA[A blog of sorts, unsorted.]]></description>
        <atom:link href="http://dougalstanton.net/rss.xml" rel="self"
                   type="application/rss+xml" />
        <lastBuildDate>Fri, 26 Dec 2014 00:00:00 UT</lastBuildDate>
        <item>
    <title>Not the worst Christmas ever!</title>
    <link>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2014-12-26-not-the-worst-christmas-ever.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>I spend Christmas day alone in the flat, cooking. For the first time I prepared a full meal for both sets of parents — our usual Christmas routine was abandoned because Helen was working until 6pm and started again on Boxing Day. Spending days away from the house was not an option.</p>
<p>I opted to cook venison instead of turkey. One, because it would mean I wasn’t playing to a rule-book and could remove items that I’m not keen on (sprouts, parsnips) without alarming anyone. Licence to play by my own rules! Also I’m not sure how well a turkey to feed seven would fit in our oven and still leave room for cooking roast potatoes, sausages and anything else required.</p>
<p>This is the first time we’ve had both sets of parents together for a sit down meal, for some reason. It went pretty well and the food was well-received. If anything we over-catered (there’s still a lot of red cabbage left over and even the small amount of broccoli wasn’t finished).</p>
<p>Due to time constraints we didn’t finish the present-opening. Helen and I still have things to give each other but I think (hope) everything that was due for other people went away with them.</p>
<p>Excuse me, I have more cold roast potatoes to eat.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Fri, 26 Dec 2014 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2014-12-26-not-the-worst-christmas-ever.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Capoeira breakdown</title>
    <link>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2014-10-19-capoeira-breakdown.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>I’ve been adding lots of new things to the <a href="http://maonochao.org" title="Mao No Chao Capoeira Scotland">Mão no Chão website</a> — with a perticular emphasis on things which have seemed important to my understanding of capoeira or that have seemed related. Talking about capoeira through other means seems so much easier than talking about capoeira in a straightforward way. (This, I think, is a very capoeira way of approaching the problem.)</p>
<p>One thing which I haven’t seen anywhere but that I’d like to see is a game breakdown. All the big sporting events get expert commentary but capoeira misses out on this — there is some academic work into the history and cultural ramifications of the art but very little covering particular instances.</p>
<p>Contrast with an article like <a href="http://www.bloodyelbow.com/2014/7/4/5869847/ufc-175-lyoto-machida-chris-weidman-mind-control-mma-technique-karate-ko-gif">Lyoto Machida’s Mind Control</a> which provides a detailed analysis of the tactics that one fighter is using to control his opponent. That is some very fine and detailed analysis and I’ve not seen anything <em>close</em> when it comes to capoeira.</p>
<p>I suppose the only answer is to do it. Stop moping about and sit down with a video of a game, watch it, watch it again, think about it, watch it in slow motion, watch it backwards — whatever it takes to make sense of everything that’s happening.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 19 Oct 2014 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2014-10-19-capoeira-breakdown.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>First lesson in Brazilian Jiu Jitsu</title>
    <link>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2014-09-27-first-lesson-in-brazilian-jiu-jitsu.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>Why BJJ? It seems interesting and it seems safe. As fascinating as boxing is it’s a clean straight path to head trauma and brain damage. BJJ, like its close cousin judo, focuses clearly on being able to stress test without causing any undue damage. (Famous last words. We’ll see what my knees can still do when I’m sixty.)</p>
<p>I went to a class at <a href="http://crosscombat.co.uk" title="BJJ, Wrestling and Kickboxing">CrossCombat</a> in Tollcross after work on Thursday, just above the Scotmid near the King’s Theatre. I arrived while they’d been doing some warm-up so didn’t see what the beginning of class looked like. And given the timings I may rarely see the class start — it just takes slightly too long to get from Haymarket station.</p>
<p>After being led through a short warm-up (standard jogging, side-steps and so on) I joined the rest of the class for a warm-up free-play, trying to maintain dominance then onto the first teaching moment, the scarf hold. Initially I was just trying to maintain the hold while my partner would escape. The people on top moved round trying out the move on different partners, then the two roles reversed. Being underneath was exhausting and felt very vulnerable. It was amazing how much weight some people seemed to exert though they looked (and claimed) to be pretty slim.</p>
<p>Next round was transitioning from the scarf hold to a north-south choke. This was more than a little daunting and even the feeling of the choke being clamped on — never mind taking effect — is quite debilitating. Also it tends to happen with your nose in some sweaty dude’s armpit which isn’t cool either.</p>
<p>Thereafter my brain hit overload, so took the executive decision to ignore all the “then you could do this, or this, or this” suggestions as clearly not aimed at me. If I could even remember the scarf hold by the end of the day it would be a miracle never mind all the other transitions. Walk don’t run.</p>
<p>The end of class was more free play though this time I had something I could positively focus on. Each person I sparred with gave me a little tip or piece of general advice: “keep your body close so you don’t give space to manoeuvre”; “turn so you’re facing your opponent when they try to move”; “keep your hands close and tight if mounted”; “relax so you don’t tire yourself out”.</p>
<p>The last point was the only one where I thought to myself, “hang on a minute, that’s not fair”. I admit outright that it makes total sense and with expertise comes the ability to relax into the game. But the game here is about positioning and since I really didn’t know what were good positions or transitions to get into them my only real intention was to frustrate the efforts of whoever I was sparring with. Without a plan of my own, I could only resist the plans of my partner. Given time I hope to relax into the situation. Then I will feel less like my muscles were given such a pummeling.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sat, 27 Sep 2014 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2014-09-27-first-lesson-in-brazilian-jiu-jitsu.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Celebrating new bike day with a Fuji Track Classic</title>
    <link>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2014-08-22-celebrating-new-bike-day.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>It’s been a long time coming but the combination of new city, new routines and a bike shop sale was enough for me to pull the trigger on a new bike — a fixed gear Fuji Track Classic. The alternative was a Charge Plug which was over £100 dearer and I didn’t think an experiment like this warranted the extra money. (Besides, I have heard more positive, or fewer negative, things said about the Fuji than the Charge bike.)</p>
<p>This is my first time with a fixed gear bike, which has been both an alarming, eye-opening, surprising and incredibly gratifying experience. I rode it (mostly) home from the shop on Monday night, which was a daunting first ride. I admit to stopping and walking it on a few of the downhill stretches because I wasn’t feeling so confident.</p>
<p>Geometrically it’s a lot more aggressive than my Ridgeback hybrid. Getting down into the drops does feel very exciting and provides an extra impression of speed. The ride is also pretty silent with no chain rattle, no jockey wheels, no creaking of mudguards or rack. For the first time I could just hear the rubber of the tyres on the road… how odd! On top of that the ride is buttery smooth. Is this the wheels, the frame design, the steel? I don’t know but I really like it.</p>
<p>Riding is a more measured and considered affair than the hybrid — getting up to speed takes longer and once you’re at speed it feels like the bike wants to stay there. The lack of coasting gives you a more nuanced impression of what the bike is doing — it is easy for bike and rider to unsynchronise when you’re pedalling through a freewheel.</p>
<p>(I am conscious that I’m anthropomorphising here. The bike does this, the bike wants that. I think because it feels wilful in its awkwardness sometimes. If you don’t settle right then you can dislodge yourself — that feels very much like you’ve just been thrown from the back of an animal. It looks like a bike but it doesn’t behave like a bike ought to, so clearly it’s being deliberately unco-operative.)</p>
<p>So how does the continual pedal pedal pedal actually feel? So far it has not been the difficult part of adjusting. As I increase the distance covered that might change. Finishing a ride feels fantastic which might be down to the endorphin buzz of the non-stop pushing; it’s not something I am conscious of when cycling with a freewheel.</p>
<p>The single gear has also not been too much of a problem. I am slowly adjusting to new personal guidelines, the most important of which is “don’t stop halfway up”. Hill climbing — particularly long steady hills — seem easier (or certainly no harder) but starting on a hill is much less fun!</p>
<p>My only regret is the colour! It’s a great looking bike but it’s gonna really show up the road dirt soon enough. I will need to have baby wipes to hand at all times. Happy riding!</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Fri, 22 Aug 2014 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2014-08-22-celebrating-new-bike-day.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Cycling to the Borders</title>
    <link>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2014-08-12-cycling-to-the-borders.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>I went on my first solo long-distance ride recently, from Edinburgh to Melrose, about 45 miles in total. The sky was largely cloudless and the wind non-existent. Apart from the dangers of dehydration and sunburn it was perfect weather for cycling.</p>
<p>Getting out of Edinburgh took too long. I started using <a href="http://www.cyclestreets.net" title="CycleStreets: cycle maps">the CycleStreets app</a> which didn’t give me any vocal directions. I was stopping on every street corner to check if I’d gone too far or needed to make a turn. Eventually the app lost my location entirely and then crashed. After restarting it was unable to continue from my current location and I was entirely sick of the whole thing. I was conscious that I had left later than I intended and every minute spent faffing with this app was a minute I wasn’t moving.</p>
<p>I fired up Google Maps and navigated the rest of the way with the Navigation feature, including voice instructions. My phone was in the back pocket of my jersey so it wasn’t always easy to hear what the voice was saying but this was still better than no voice at all. In future I would use headphones and have the nearside earbud in for instructions while keeping the other ear open for traffic.</p>
<p>I was trying to stop as little as possible so didn’t really lunch. I had two sandwiches and a caramel wafer with me but didn’t take the time to halt and rest properly. This was (obviously) a mistake. I should also have stopped somewhere to get a water refill. Instead I wasted time trying to get through the back entrance to Dalkeith Country Park. It seems to be part of NCN1 but had been padlocked. Thankfully a driver was there waiting for someone to let him through and he helped me <a href="https://www.google.co.uk/maps/@55.921969,-3.060568,3a,75y,118.13h,84.08t/data=!3m4!1e1!3m2!1s146hJKISFpgm-Qk0gE7_aw!2e0">lift the bike over the 7ft gate</a> into the park.</p>
<p>There were several good stretches of path coming out of Edinburgh to the east and heading south past Musselburgh and through Dalkeith. From there I was in the hills above the A7 almost the whole way to Galashiels. The roads were really quiet but in excellent condition — at no point did I feel stressed by the traffic while travelling through the hills. It was just me and the inclines and the declines.</p>
<p>The pain started to kick in about forty minutes from my destination. My little toe stopped appreciating the pressure from the pedalling action inside my shoe. The long hours in the saddle took their toll. I felt really relieved during the last stretch into Melrose, down hill all the way and clear of cars.</p>
<p>I rolled past the Melrose town markers at bang on 6 o’clock, some 4¼ hours after leaving the house. The average speed for the whole journey was about 10mph but this isn’t at all indicative of actual travelling speeds. The first hour was so stop-start I probably did less than 5mph whereas there were sections on freshly laid A7 with a tailwind where I’d be travelling more than 20mph. In future I’ll remember to use an app which tracks location and time and speed properly.</p>
<p>It was an amazing ride and I am much wiser now about the availability of cycle-friendly roads and trails. The obvious next step is to do a similar route but take more time: time to admire the scenery; time to take photos; time to eat lunch; time to deviate from the path if a tea room or interesting tourist attraction is signposted. Time to <a href="http://bikeridebooks.co.uk/a-bit-scott-ish/">hunt down that lemon drizzle cake</a>.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Tue, 12 Aug 2014 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2014-08-12-cycling-to-the-borders.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>How many bicycles is too many?</title>
    <link>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2014-08-05-how-many-bicycles-is-too-many.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>The saying goes that you always need one more bike than you have. Well, initially I didn’t think I needed a bike at all but that assumption turned out to be wrong<a href="#fn1" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref1"><sup>1</sup></a>. Since then I’ve been discovering the ways in which my one bikes can help me out. Commuting every day, taking less time and able to carry much more to and from work. Carrying incredible amounts of shopping easily from the supermarket to home. Going on holiday for a week in Islay and Arran entirely under our own steam. Jetting across town to meet people, visit places and get around quickly.</p>
<p>The <a href="http://www.velominati.com/the-rules/#12" title="You always need one more bike">incredibly serious Rules</a> tell us that we always need another bike and I’m slowly coming to the conclusion that when you own 1 bike you probably need 2. (I will hold off judgement on the full implication.) My current bike plays the role of the generalist very well but I’m looking to specialise a bit. My long term plan is essentially to split my current bike into two bikes — one playing the role of the heavy duty workhorse that will let me get the shopping, take a full load of panniers on the road and be equipped for long journeys. The other would play the role of something light and simple for local riding, when I just want to jump on the bike and go.</p>
<p>I’ve been conscious for some time that I don’t get to wear some of my clothes when I’m cycling. Cycling wear ends up meaning technical wear when I leave the house and I want to stop that. I don’t walk to the shops with hiking boots and a pole so why should I cycle with the equivalent? Now that’s not to say I actually do <a href="http://edinburghcyclechic.wordpress.com/" title="Because you don&#39;t have to wear Lycra">wear lycra to hop on the bike</a> —</p>
<p>To that end I’ve been looking at something a bit minimalist and more stylish. It doesn’t always have to be about hard work, after all. I really like the idea of slim single-speed bike with none of the mess that I have on my current bike to spoil the look. I fear in practise that things like weather, luggage, lights and so on will minimise the extent to which this can be achieved. We don’t all live in California… but I’ve been putting some thought to what it would mean if we did.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr />
<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>How did I go so long living in Edinburgh without a bike? Why did nobody grab me by the shoulders and tell me I was missing out? Getting the bus seemed a reasonable way to move around when I wasn’t just walking.<a href="#fnref1">↩</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2014 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2014-08-05-how-many-bicycles-is-too-many.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>The Swedish author with the bolt from the blue</title>
    <link>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2014-06-25-swedish-bolt-from-the-blue.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>I’ve mentioned in the past being unimpressed with <em>The Girl with the Dragon Tattoo</em> and suspecting that the translation was a good chunk of the problem. I remember thinking that the prose seemed very cliched and relied heavily on hackneyed sayings that shouldn’t be a part of a well-written novel. Since we can hardly blame the author of the Swedish original for the clunky English phrasing we’ll have to point the finger at the translator.</p>
<p>Maybe you think I’m being unfair. While on holiday recently I had time to read the two sequels and got the same impression with them as I did with the original book. And since they’re fresh in my mind I still remember some of the dodgy phrases. Let’s see if I can demonstrate some problems.</p>
<p>The English translations seem very fond of describing sudden events in the same lumpen way. There’s a couple from the first book, though not the only ones.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The question came like a bolt out of the blue, but Berger did not seem the least bit surprised.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Forgive me for bothering you out of the blue, but I happened to be in St. Albans, and I tried to call you during the day.”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>From the sequel, <em>The Girl who Played with Fire</em>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>And then out of the blue she had destroyed him. She had struck back with a power and determination that he had not dreamed she possessed. She had humiliated him. She had tortured him. She had all but demolished him.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Hedström said nothing during the taxi journey from Slussen to Kungsholmen. He was in a daze from out of the blue ending up in a real police investigation. He glanced at Bohman, who was reading Armansky’s presentation again.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>And finally from <em>The Girl who Kicked the Hornet’s Nest</em></p>
<blockquote>
<p>“Annika… this isn’t the way I had planned to end my time at Millennium. In the middle of chaos. But the offer came like a bolt from the blue, and I can’t say no. I mean, it’s the chance of a lifetime. I got the offer just before Dag and Mia were shot, and there’s been such turmoil here that I buried it. And now I have the world’s worst guilty conscience.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>At 6:00 she paid her bill and walked to Lillian’s place on Olivedalsgatan. She punched in the door code her friend had given her. She stepped into the stairwell and was looking for a light switch when the attack came out of the blue. She was slammed up against a tiled wall next to the door. She banged her head hard, felt a rush of pain, and fell to the ground.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I think you begin to see what I’m talking about. You read these phrases — and others like “within a few minutes he would be dead as a door-nail” — and wonder to yourself what the translator and editor were doing. There are dozens like these and they often break the illusion. Who carefully describes a method of killing someone that will result in them being “dead as a door-nail”?</p>
<p>It gives hope for the rest of us. Between dodgy translations of Stieg Larsson and the top-notch output of Dan Brown there’s room for everyone in the airport thriller market, whether you can write or not.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jun 2014 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2014-06-25-swedish-bolt-from-the-blue.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Grammar of movement (reprise) &mdash; Contact Jam</title>
    <link>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2014-04-11-grammar-of-movement-reprise.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>Last weekend I finally screwed my courage to the sticking place and went along to <a href="https://www.facebook.com/groups/493304847398335/" title="Glasgow Jam Facebook page">Glasgow Jam</a>, an afternoon of contact improvisation and artistic jamming of other kinds.</p>
<p><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Contact_improvisation" title="Contact improvisation described, if not defined">Contact improvisation</a> is a dance form in the loosest sense. Wikipedia describes it as postmodern dance, which doesn’t help much. It’s interesting to me because it’s like a particular aspect of capoeira (the close-contact floor movement) without the martial intent. You move around and over and through each other, maintaining contact and exploring the way in which two (or more) people can interact. It’s entirely unchoreographed so you can just get stuck in there. There was a four-year-old child at the session too; it’s easy to do something if you’re willing to let yourself be loose. It reminded me a great deal of trust/contact exercises I’ve done with various drama groups over the years.</p>
<p>The session lasted 3 hours without any particular structure after the warm-up period. People would dip in and out of the floor to take a break, get water, or even play instruments and paint as part of the “jam” experience. Apart from these off-the-cuff musical additions there was no soundtrack. We were dancing in silence which I found unsettling at times — and not easy to get into. There were also a lot of “serious” expressions from the participants; I really couldn’t tell whether enjoying oneself was verboten or whether this was just the face everyone used when they concentrated. Or maybe they were always bored when “contacting” with me…</p>
<p>The session provided exactly the challenges that I expected it would. In light of my <a href="2014-04-05-grammar-of-movement.html" title="Grammar of movement: getting stuck in a rut">previous reflections on being stuck in a movement rut</a>, this was a great activity to highlight where my assumptions are. I had initially been worried that my instinct from capoeira would sneak in and I would pull someone’s leg out from under them without thinking! Thankfully that part of my capoeira game didn’t cross over but lots of other parts did. My biggest problem was being very uncomfortable touching the ground and otherwise being put into a vulnerable position. I was continually conscious of my need to be planted and in control — in short, not to surrender my trust to my dance partner. It took me over an hour of work to become comfortable with sitting on the ground, if you can believe that.</p>
<p>This follows neatly what I had said previously about ungrammatical movements — I’m so ingrained in the capoeira way that even when I try it’s really hard to embrace touching the ground with other body parts. On top of that I often found myself being, if not openly hostile, then antagonistic. Instead of an improvised dance I was making it quite game-like to see how the other person would react. Again, I found this hard to avoid but I’m sure it got quite annoying after a while.</p>
<p>Ultimately I had some problems trying to determine who the jam was for. It was billed as a participant-only event. There was no viewing gallery and it wasn’t a show. So in that respect it was for the dancers themselves — but it seemed so serious. There was no emotional interaction between people: no laughing, no whoops, no eye contact, no talking. I would like to return and see if I can improvise these more than anything else.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Fri, 11 Apr 2014 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2014-04-11-grammar-of-movement-reprise.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Grammar of movement</title>
    <link>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2014-04-05-grammar-of-movement.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>I wrote recently about <a href="/posts/2014-02-17-critical-appraisal-from-the-inside.html" title="My thoughts on Phil&#39;s performance at Conflux PITCH">Phil’s performance at the Conflux PITCH event</a> and how I had a hard time writing a meaningful critical appraisal. One of the issues was seeing the capoeira inside his performance and not being able to see past that.</p>
<p>One of the other performers that day was <a href="http://www.iamscotthouston.com/" title="Scott Houston&#39;s home page">Scott Houston</a>. Superficially he appears to share a lot of the same movements but it appears from his biography online that he has no capoeira training. He’s probably come across capoeira but it’s not a meaningful part of his background. Can we tell this by watching the way he moves? I think we can and it’s most obvious in this video, <em>Alive</em>.</p>
<iframe width="560" height="315" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/oBh7ASo1UIE" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>

<p>Like learning a language you pick up a great deal of capoeira through imitation rather than explicit instruction. The challenge of anyone learning capoeira or anything else by imitation is learning to identify what are the real rules and what are just things which your role models don’t do — things which you can’t learn by imitation because you don’t have anyone to imitate<a href="#fn1" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref1"><sup>1</sup></a>. Like a language, capoeira has a “grammar” and much of it is learned implicitly. After a while we all begin to speak (or move) in ways which are in tune with what we’re doing — the grammar becomes internalised and we no longer think “does this sound/feel right?”.</p>
<p>I think one of the main differences between Phil and Scott’s performances was that Phil has the capoeira grammar deep in his movement and has to struggle more to overcome that. (I predict that if I had any knowledge of gymnastics or Shotokan Karate then I might see their influence on Scott Houston’s movement. Any takers?) The director/ choreographer who spoke at the Conflux event mentioned specifically that he likes using artists outside their comfort zone to avoid the ingrained behaviours from taking over. Dancers always end up standing in the classic ballet postures — toes pointed, arms slight bent. Gymnasts have their own favoured postures and so on with all the other physical performance artists. Using people who haven’t been trained specifically produces a looseness of interpretation — at least according to this director’s opinion.</p>
<p>From the perspective of someone trying to learn capoeira this is also important. The movement culture in Scotland and Brazil is different — Scottish dance and Brazilian dance emphasise very different things in posture, for example. Unlearning the way in which we move and hold our bodies is almost even harder — I’ve been standing and walking this way in this mould my entire life, since I was old enough to imitate the movement of my parents. Seeing total capoeira beginners with experience of other movement forms brings other fascinating layers to the mix — whether they’ve done Taekwondo or belly dancing the outcome is something bold and original. And bringing something new to it is what we should all strive for!</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr />
<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>This is why I think it’s really important to have many role models in a class. Different people of different shapes and sizes who have different preferences for the ways in which they move — not only do you see a wider range of possibilities from which to synthesise your own style but you can also see how people play to their strengths and overcome their weaknesses — be it fitness, height, strength, or something else.<a href="#fnref1">↩</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sat, 05 Apr 2014 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2014-04-05-grammar-of-movement.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Getting rid of bikes. Is that even allowed?</title>
    <link>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2014-03-30-getting-rid-of-bikes.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>Ha! In direct contravention of <a href="http://www.velominati.com/the-rules/#12" title="Rule 12">rule number twelve</a> we just got rid of two bikes. That probably means the number of bikes we need stands at N+2 just to reach parity with where we were yesterday. We do have a lot more space in the hallway now, which is nice!</p>
<p>The decluttering is part one (the easy part) of preparations to move back to Edinburgh. More on that as we get closer to the departure point.</p>
<p>The bikes — Helen’s old bike and my old bike — went to the Glasgow Bike Station. My bike was bought from the Edinburgh Bike Station a few years ago to see if cycling would be a reasonable addition to my commute. Since then there was been no looking back (well, except to check traffic over my shoulder). Helen’s old bike was won by her gran in a raffle and she’s had it over fifteen years! So it was a more important moment to pass her bike on.</p>
<p>Riding down there was really scary, which surprised me. The whole feel of the bike which used to be my daily transport was totally alien because I’d not used it for more than a year. The geometry was odd. The handlebar felt too short, the position of the pedals was different and the circle they made seemed smaller than my current bike. The pedals were simple platforms and I kept trying to adjust my foot position as if there were toe traps. On top of that the brake blocks were pretty close to the nub so I wasn’t in the least confident that I could really pull off an emergency stop if required. Helen nearly fell off before starting, by instinctively reaching for drop bars which didn’t exist and tipping through the bike! But we both made the journey in one piece and walked away for afternoon tea at The Hidden Lane Tea Room.</p>
<p>The Bike Station will be able to refurbish or cannabalise the bikes as necessary and sell on bikes to more people, like me, looking for a cheap bike to get around.</p>
<p>I’ll have to think about what the N+2 might be for another blog post…</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 30 Mar 2014 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2014-03-30-getting-rid-of-bikes.html</guid>
</item>

    </channel> 
</rss>
