<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>Looking Out To Sea</title>
        <link>http://dougalstanton.net</link>
        <description><![CDATA[A blog of sorts, unsorted.]]></description>
        <atom:link href="http://dougalstanton.net/rss.xml" rel="self"
                   type="application/rss+xml" />
        <lastBuildDate>Wed, 11 Mar 2015 00:00:00 UT</lastBuildDate>
        <item>
    <title>Bike fit at Bike Craft (part 1)</title>
    <link>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2015-03-11-bike-fit-at-bike-craft-part-1.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>Since I got my first bike as an adult several years ago I noticed that I pedal with my feet on the outside of the pedals, splayed slightly outwards. This wasn’t a particular problem with flat pedals but if I am using toe clips or straps my legs felt uncomfortable and twisted. After a day of cycling I got pain behind my knee, particularly at the back of my right leg.</p>
<p>Doing the research pointed up an issue of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Q_factor_%28bicycles%29" title="Q factor for bicycles">“Q factor”</a>, the distance between the two planes in which the pedals move. Different bike designs (mountain, road, leisure) will differ due to bottom bracket size, the splay of the cranks and so on. But the racier the bike the narrower the distance between your feet.</p>
<p>Reasoning that my natural/desired Q factor was wider than one afforded by the design of my bike, I bought some <a href="http://www.specialized.com/gb/gb/ftb/mtb-components/pedals/body-geometry-pedal-axle-extenders" title="Pedal extenders (larger than life)">pedal extenders</a> — metal cylinders with a pedal-style male thread at one end and a crank-style female thread at the other. This seemed to solve the issue: my foot could be strapped in and I could pedal pedal pedal for hours without pain.</p>
<p>So where is this going? It’s going the way of all hacks, all “self-medication”. The niggling belief that there was something fundamentally wrong with my setup that I was not fixing but shifting elsewhere with the pedal extenders. With every new bike I buy, or every new saddle, or pedals, do I have to go through these experiments?</p>
<p>I arranged a fitting at <a href="http://bikecraftedinburgh.co.uk/" title="Bike Craft, Edinburgh">Bike Craft on Ferry Road</a>. They asked me about my cycling habits and distances, and the all important list of problems and aches I get. Then they set me up on a massage table to measure the flexibility of my hips. I knew this would be pretty terrible; despite the BJJ and capoeira I am still a stiff old board.</p>
<p>With all this data gathered I sat on my own bike on a trainer and made some adjustments, making sure to take before and after measurements. The seatpost was replaced with another that had a smaller offset — since my saddle was at its furthest forward to counteract the existing post’s large rearward offset. The saddle height was reduced. And the pedal extenders were removed.</p>
<p>I’ve got the temporary seatpost on loan for a few days to see how it works with the new height and without the pedal extenders. After all of the adjustments of the evening, and the unfamiliarity of my new riding position, I was unable to definitely say if it was better or worse than my usual position.</p>
<p>Initial impressions are that I feel more “inside” the bike. It feels more likely that I could get a higher cadence in this position, which does hint that I was too far away from the pedals before. I’ll give it a few days and a few more miles to see what happens.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Wed, 11 Mar 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2015-03-11-bike-fit-at-bike-craft-part-1.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Welcome my Son in full</title>
    <link>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2015-03-07-welcome-my-son-in-full.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>Just over a year ago we saw <a href="/posts/2014-02-17-critical-appraisal-from-the-inside.html">Phil, of Spotted Stripes Circus fame, perform the beginnings of something built on the story of Frankenstein</a>. On the first of March I had the considerable pleasure of seeing the first public performance of <em>Welcome my Son</em>.</p>
<p>There was a feedback form, so this is a record of what I wrote.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Was there any single element that particularly stood out positively?</p>
<p>The physical characterisation of the ‘monster’ was fantastic, particularly the involuntary jerks and convulsions. It was uncomfortable to watch (I found myself flinching in sympathy) and amazing to see that combined with the control to manage it while still hanging on a pole or balancing on the scaffold.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Was there any single element that stood out negatively?</p>
<p>The transition from the physical theatre at the start, with just the subtlest of sounds to support it, to a traditional soliloquy, was a bit jarring at first. I hadn’t expected it so I took a minute to adjust to the change in pace.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Overall what would have made the performance better?</p>
<p>The contrast between the two characters got a bit confused at the finale, when I wasn’t totally clear who was speaking which part until it settled into a rhythm. If that were made clearer it might be easier to understand the climax as it happens rather than needing a moment to reflect on what is going on.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Would you go and see this show again?</p>
<p>I don’t normally see shows again but I think if I were to go again I would enjoy re-examining what I saw and looking for new details.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Would you recommend it to anyone else?</p>
<p>I would definitely recommend this show — indeed I have already recommended it to someone, though I was not able to say when or if it would next be performed.</p>
</blockquote>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sat, 07 Mar 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2015-03-07-welcome-my-son-in-full.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Taking the long way home</title>
    <link>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2015-01-14-taking-the-long-way-home.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>I decided I couldn’t face another wrestle with the Calton Road/Leith Street/Picardy Place/Leith Walk snarl-up and decided to find something more relaxed. Every time I looked up cycling to the western edge of Edinburgh there seemed to be a route which skirted the north of the city and came back down about Haymarket. So where was it actually, and could I get there?</p>
<iframe height='405' width='590' frameborder='0' allowtransparency='true' scrolling='no' src='https://www.strava.com/activities/241037592/embed/567351eef61b1487465e53d0e8f24cbdcab17ce3'></iframe>

<p>It turns out to be pretty easy to find from Haymarket station — though I did have some help because there was an old guy on a Brompton who was also heading that direction so I just tailgated him. Brompton or not, he quickly disappeared into the distance…</p>
<p>I’m still nursing a sore wrist from earlier in the week, so I was effectively riding “one-handed” (but not really; I could still brake or steer with both if necessary). So I wasn’t really riding <em>fast</em> though when there’s no traffic lights and a decent road surface you can get up a decent pace. From the Strava chart I reckon the uninterrupted section of road was averaging ~25kph — about 15mph.</p>
<p>More importantly the “moving time” was about half an hour — which means in half an hour I can get to Haymarket station without touching the roads, and that’s if I’m not pushing it. I’ve been lamenting that my cycle commute has been getting shorter as the years go by, but I’ve not been willing to do the full ride from flat to office. I’m still too feart of being stranded in the middle of West Lothian somewhere especially in the winter. (And I don’t trust the traffic on that road either.)</p>
<p>This seems like the ideal way to add some more miles to my weekly tally without going crazy.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2015-01-14-taking-the-long-way-home.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Cycling like your granny</title>
    <link>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2015-01-12-cycling-like-your-granny.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>At the weekend I ventured out into some pretty foul weather for a trip to Hermiston Gait<a href="#fn1" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref1"><sup>1</sup></a>. According to Google Maps I could follow the NEPN for a chunk and get there in forty minutes. I set off at a relaxed pace and got lost. (I see now that I followed my nose and headed west along the Water of Leith at one point when I should have headed east and curved back on the cycle path.) But I had a successful shopping trip and was largely stress free while doing it.</p>
<p>It was my first visit to Hermiston Gait and Edinburgh Park station. In the summer I can definitely see myself hopping off the train there for a gentle ride back into town. The new shared path that runs alongside the tram is really relaxing compared to the stress of road travel. Cycling as it should be.</p>
<p>On my return journey I came a more direct route — past Haymarket, along Shandwick Place and into George Street before home. It was still raining and I was passed several times by cyclists in a hurry. I was trying my best to remain at a sedate pace; all the off-road travel I was doing certainly helped.</p>
<p>There’s a phrase on the City Cycling Edinburgh forums about <a href="http://citycyclingedinburgh.info/bbpress/topic.php?id=5723" title="National &#39;ride like your gran&#39; day">“cycling like your granny”</a>. This amounts to <em>not</em> battling with traffic and seeing how you travel. Limiting yourself to 10mph or coasting otherwise. The weekend’s trip on quiet segregated routes helped bring me closer to the relaxed mood I would have to be in to ride like that all the time.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr />
<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>I can assure you that it’s no more exciting than you imagine it is.<a href="#fnref1">↩</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2015-01-12-cycling-like-your-granny.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Teaching styles in capoeira and BJJ</title>
    <link>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2015-01-09-teaching-capoeira-bjj.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>It’s been about two months now since I started Brazilian Jiu-Jitsu so I’ve got a better understanding of how it’s being taught now.</p>
<p>I’m really impressed with the teaching at Cross Combat, and I can tell it’s something that William and his team take a fair amount of pride in. It seems to rely on a few fundamentals:</p>
<ul>
<li>Focus on one thing per class</li>
<li>Building technique piecemeal</li>
<li>Progressive resistance</li>
</ul>
<p>Nothing that seems outlandish, unusual or revolutionary but the reality is that it’s <em>productive</em>. On top of this there is some philosophical approach which emphasises exploration and flow over exacting instruction.</p>
<p>The attitude is very similar to the teaching in capoeira (at least, in Mão No Chão) but the actual teaching is very different structure is very different. We definitely <em>don’t</em> focus on a single thing during a lesson — a scattergun approach would be a more accurate description.</p>
<p>I think we try for progressive resistance but miss the full value. We can start off very collaborative but there’s no steady progression from there. A predictable next step for each level of resistance would be valuable to have: in this way it’s always obvious how the other person will react. On that topic a prohibition against <em>malicia</em> and <em>malandragem</em> during training until it’s explicitly allowed. Indeed, that is a level of resistance that can be saved for an actual game.</p>
<p>It’s the end of the Christmas holidays and several weeks since I’ve done any capoeira or been to a class. I’m going to rethink everything I have written here in light of what we actually do the next time I train.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Fri, 09 Jan 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2015-01-09-teaching-capoeira-bjj.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Happy to agree, happy to disagree</title>
    <link>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2014-12-31-happy-to-agree-happy-to-disagree.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>I’ve been watching a lot of clips recently from the Mark Kermode/Simon Mayo review slot on Radio 5 Live. The radio reviews are <a href="https://www.youtube.com/user/kermodeandmayo/" title="Kermode &amp; Mayo&#39;s Film Reviews">filmed and broadcast on their Youtube channel</a> so you can see the full interaction and gesticulation of Mark Kermode.</p>
<p>I’m not the kind of person who seeks out reviews for films I want to watch. If the trailer or word-of-mouth suggests it’s good or interesting I’ll give it a go. But I <em>do</em> like comparing reviews of films that I’ve seen because it’s good to get others’ perspectives, particularly the views of people who are actually immersed in film as viewers.</p>
<p>I mostly agree with Mark Kermode’s views but the interesting point, which I’ve yet to really explain, is that I don’t mind when we disagree. Partly because he is often very clear that the context of any film review is as subjective as the film-going experience: personal mood, expectations, comfortable seating, well, it all makes a difference. His reviews are as coloured by that subjectivity as mine are so we both have a get-out-of-jail-free card.</p>
<p>Of course one of the real delights about any critic is to see them really slating something. Not a film that they think is not much fun but something they think is really terrible — which for Mark Kermode generally means “a Michael Bay movie”.</p>
<iframe width="420" height="315" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/v0d6G1X278s" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>

<p>So I invite you to watch his review of Michael Bay’s live-action <em>Transformers</em> movie. And despite being a fan of the 80s cartoon feature he briefly mentions I thought this was a terrible movie.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Wed, 31 Dec 2014 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2014-12-31-happy-to-agree-happy-to-disagree.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Not the worst Christmas ever!</title>
    <link>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2014-12-26-not-the-worst-christmas-ever.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>I spend Christmas day alone in the flat, cooking. For the first time I prepared a full meal for both sets of parents — our usual Christmas routine was abandoned because Helen was working until 6pm and started again on Boxing Day. Spending days away from the house was not an option.</p>
<p>I opted to cook venison instead of turkey. One, because it would mean I wasn’t playing to a rule-book and could remove items that I’m not keen on (sprouts, parsnips) without alarming anyone. Licence to play by my own rules! Also I’m not sure how well a turkey to feed seven would fit in our oven and still leave room for cooking roast potatoes, sausages and anything else required.</p>
<p>This is the first time we’ve had both sets of parents together for a sit down meal, for some reason. It went pretty well and the food was well-received. If anything we over-catered (there’s still a lot of red cabbage left over and even the small amount of broccoli wasn’t finished).</p>
<p>Due to time constraints we didn’t finish the present-opening. Helen and I still have things to give each other but I think (hope) everything that was due for other people went away with them.</p>
<p>Excuse me, I have more cold roast potatoes to eat.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Fri, 26 Dec 2014 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2014-12-26-not-the-worst-christmas-ever.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Capoeira breakdown</title>
    <link>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2014-10-19-capoeira-breakdown.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>I’ve been adding lots of new things to the <a href="http://maonochao.org" title="Mao No Chao Capoeira Scotland">Mão no Chão website</a> — with a perticular emphasis on things which have seemed important to my understanding of capoeira or that have seemed related. Talking about capoeira through other means seems so much easier than talking about capoeira in a straightforward way. (This, I think, is a very capoeira way of approaching the problem.)</p>
<p>One thing which I haven’t seen anywhere but that I’d like to see is a game breakdown. All the big sporting events get expert commentary but capoeira misses out on this — there is some academic work into the history and cultural ramifications of the art but very little covering particular instances.</p>
<p>Contrast with an article like <a href="http://www.bloodyelbow.com/2014/7/4/5869847/ufc-175-lyoto-machida-chris-weidman-mind-control-mma-technique-karate-ko-gif">Lyoto Machida’s Mind Control</a> which provides a detailed analysis of the tactics that one fighter is using to control his opponent. That is some very fine and detailed analysis and I’ve not seen anything <em>close</em> when it comes to capoeira.</p>
<p>I suppose the only answer is to do it. Stop moping about and sit down with a video of a game, watch it, watch it again, think about it, watch it in slow motion, watch it backwards — whatever it takes to make sense of everything that’s happening.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 19 Oct 2014 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2014-10-19-capoeira-breakdown.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>First lesson in Brazilian Jiu Jitsu</title>
    <link>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2014-09-27-first-lesson-in-brazilian-jiu-jitsu.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>Why BJJ? It seems interesting and it seems safe. As fascinating as boxing is it’s a clean straight path to head trauma and brain damage. BJJ, like its close cousin judo, focuses clearly on being able to stress test without causing any undue damage. (Famous last words. We’ll see what my knees can still do when I’m sixty.)</p>
<p>I went to a class at <a href="http://crosscombat.co.uk" title="BJJ, Wrestling and Kickboxing">CrossCombat</a> in Tollcross after work on Thursday, just above the Scotmid near the King’s Theatre. I arrived while they’d been doing some warm-up so didn’t see what the beginning of class looked like. And given the timings I may rarely see the class start — it just takes slightly too long to get from Haymarket station.</p>
<p>After being led through a short warm-up (standard jogging, side-steps and so on) I joined the rest of the class for a warm-up free-play, trying to maintain dominance then onto the first teaching moment, the scarf hold. Initially I was just trying to maintain the hold while my partner would escape. The people on top moved round trying out the move on different partners, then the two roles reversed. Being underneath was exhausting and felt very vulnerable. It was amazing how much weight some people seemed to exert though they looked (and claimed) to be pretty slim.</p>
<p>Next round was transitioning from the scarf hold to a north-south choke. This was more than a little daunting and even the feeling of the choke being clamped on — never mind taking effect — is quite debilitating. Also it tends to happen with your nose in some sweaty dude’s armpit which isn’t cool either.</p>
<p>Thereafter my brain hit overload, so took the executive decision to ignore all the “then you could do this, or this, or this” suggestions as clearly not aimed at me. If I could even remember the scarf hold by the end of the day it would be a miracle never mind all the other transitions. Walk don’t run.</p>
<p>The end of class was more free play though this time I had something I could positively focus on. Each person I sparred with gave me a little tip or piece of general advice: “keep your body close so you don’t give space to manoeuvre”; “turn so you’re facing your opponent when they try to move”; “keep your hands close and tight if mounted”; “relax so you don’t tire yourself out”.</p>
<p>The last point was the only one where I thought to myself, “hang on a minute, that’s not fair”. I admit outright that it makes total sense and with expertise comes the ability to relax into the game. But the game here is about positioning and since I really didn’t know what were good positions or transitions to get into them my only real intention was to frustrate the efforts of whoever I was sparring with. Without a plan of my own, I could only resist the plans of my partner. Given time I hope to relax into the situation. Then I will feel less like my muscles were given such a pummeling.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sat, 27 Sep 2014 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2014-09-27-first-lesson-in-brazilian-jiu-jitsu.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Celebrating new bike day with a Fuji Track Classic</title>
    <link>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2014-08-22-celebrating-new-bike-day.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>It’s been a long time coming but the combination of new city, new routines and a bike shop sale was enough for me to pull the trigger on a new bike — a fixed gear Fuji Track Classic. The alternative was a Charge Plug which was over £100 dearer and I didn’t think an experiment like this warranted the extra money. (Besides, I have heard more positive, or fewer negative, things said about the Fuji than the Charge bike.)</p>
<p>This is my first time with a fixed gear bike, which has been both an alarming, eye-opening, surprising and incredibly gratifying experience. I rode it (mostly) home from the shop on Monday night, which was a daunting first ride. I admit to stopping and walking it on a few of the downhill stretches because I wasn’t feeling so confident.</p>
<p>Geometrically it’s a lot more aggressive than my Ridgeback hybrid. Getting down into the drops does feel very exciting and provides an extra impression of speed. The ride is also pretty silent with no chain rattle, no jockey wheels, no creaking of mudguards or rack. For the first time I could just hear the rubber of the tyres on the road… how odd! On top of that the ride is buttery smooth. Is this the wheels, the frame design, the steel? I don’t know but I really like it.</p>
<p>Riding is a more measured and considered affair than the hybrid — getting up to speed takes longer and once you’re at speed it feels like the bike wants to stay there. The lack of coasting gives you a more nuanced impression of what the bike is doing — it is easy for bike and rider to unsynchronise when you’re pedalling through a freewheel.</p>
<p>(I am conscious that I’m anthropomorphising here. The bike does this, the bike wants that. I think because it feels wilful in its awkwardness sometimes. If you don’t settle right then you can dislodge yourself — that feels very much like you’ve just been thrown from the back of an animal. It looks like a bike but it doesn’t behave like a bike ought to, so clearly it’s being deliberately unco-operative.)</p>
<p>So how does the continual pedal pedal pedal actually feel? So far it has not been the difficult part of adjusting. As I increase the distance covered that might change. Finishing a ride feels fantastic which might be down to the endorphin buzz of the non-stop pushing; it’s not something I am conscious of when cycling with a freewheel.</p>
<p>The single gear has also not been too much of a problem. I am slowly adjusting to new personal guidelines, the most important of which is “don’t stop halfway up”. Hill climbing — particularly long steady hills — seem easier (or certainly no harder) but starting on a hill is much less fun!</p>
<p>My only regret is the colour! It’s a great looking bike but it’s gonna really show up the road dirt soon enough. I will need to have baby wipes to hand at all times. Happy riding!</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Fri, 22 Aug 2014 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2014-08-22-celebrating-new-bike-day.html</guid>
</item>

    </channel> 
</rss>
