<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>Looking Out To Sea</title>
        <link>http://dougalstanton.net</link>
        <description><![CDATA[A blog of sorts, unsorted.]]></description>
        <atom:link href="http://dougalstanton.net/rss.xml" rel="self"
                   type="application/rss+xml" />
        <lastBuildDate>Thu, 26 Sep 2013 00:00:00 UT</lastBuildDate>
        <item>
    <title>Mestre Marrom workshop in London</title>
    <link>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2013-09-26-marrom-workshop-in-london.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>Mestre Marrom was in north London doing a capoeira workshop at the weekend (20–22 September 2013). Various people from Mao No Chao went down from Scotland. I took the sleeper bus down on the Friday night with a handful of others and we arrived in London at 7am. Luckily we had planned for this and made enquiries of the best greasy spoon to get breakfast near to the workshop venue. Somewhere called Crystal Cafe in Homerton, I think.</p>
<p>I’d never met Marrom so this was a first. There were a lot of people from many London groups and further afield too. The hall was slightly too small for the number of people. When we were working in lines it was easy for the people at the edges of the rooms to run out of space when travelling sideways or backwards. It also made seeing across the crowd of people difficult.</p>
<p>We did some bits of pair work, and some sequences down the hall singly and in pairs. Then a double roda with a single bateria and at the end of each day a full roda. A number of local mestres came in for this — it was good to see them play — Fantasma, Axe, Joaozinho, Polaco and probably others who I forget. It was great to see all the different styles of play.</p>
<p>Overall I felt totally out of place being there. The level of skill was so far out of reach for me that I was just getting in the way. I basically spent the whole weekend uncomfortable and anxious without really taking anything in.</p>
<p>Marrom’s capoeira is very direct and grounded. It doesn’t give much away. Apart from ground — I often thought he escaped a long way out of an attack, often to re-enter very quickly with a hard attack. But quick chapas were something of a theme, both of his style and the weekend.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Thu, 26 Sep 2013 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2013-09-26-marrom-workshop-in-london.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>The game is a reflection of the players</title>
    <link>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2013-09-09-the-game-is-a-reflection-of-the-players.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>I enter the roda wanting to play elegantly and beautifully — wanting to be in control of myself. If the other person is playing at a level where I don’t feel threatened then I can concentrate on myself, and how the interaction feels. But when the pressure is turned up I concentrate on being in control of the other person. If the other person is playing above my level and I feel threatened then the urge to “fight back” starts to dominate. I start to lose what little control I had over myself in a futile attempt at mastery over the situation.</p>
<p>This has wider implications than just my growth as a capoeirista. The immediate requirements — to try twice as hard to play really well and be in control of myself, and let everything else fall out as it may — are fairly clear. Being more comfortable with my shortcomings and all that.</p>
<p>But there is more than that. This is the roda as a microcosm for life and social interaction. This illustrates how I react when I’m out of my depth. I would rather fake it than be honest about my shortcomings: in the roda I will be slapdash and uncontrolled rather than controlled but underwhelming; in life I would rather remain silent and appear competent than ask questions. I would rather appear angry than incompetent.</p>
<hr />
<p>A common interview question is to ask about weaknesses. What the real intention behind this question is nobody knows any more. Some people recommend trying to spin a positive to seem like a bad thing (“oh I’m too hard working”) while others say this is too obvious and you should be honest but show how you mitigate this. I suppose we can all agree that admitting to kleptomania or torturing kittens will probably not go in your favour.</p>
<p>What nobody talks about is that spotting your own flaws can be really incredibly difficult. They are hard to spot and harder to admit to yourself as real problems. Just writing the above passages is quite painful, even though in hindsight <em>I always knew this to be true</em>. I can think of countless scenarios where they apply.</p>
<p>I don’t know what I will do in the future with this extra level of self-knowledge.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Mon, 09 Sep 2013 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2013-09-09-the-game-is-a-reflection-of-the-players.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>A new yeast project: brewing</title>
    <link>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2013-08-23-a-new-yeast-project-brewing.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>Since moving to Glasgow we’ve been lumbered with a terrible oven which doesn’t get hot enough to really do justice to bread baking. Instead I decided to go different avenue and try some home brewing. It’s yeast Jim, but not as we know it.</p>
<p>I bought a fermenting bucket, a plastic tube, hydrometer, thermometer and airlock from the good people at <a href="http://www.innhousebrewery.co.uk/" title="Innhouse Brewery Company">Glasgow’s eminent homebrew shop</a>. Alongside that I bought the ingredients for a Canadian lager. A friend at work donated some used beer bottles and the use of his crown capper.</p>
<p>My two obstacles were cleanliness and temperature. Getting and keeping everything sterilised is a hard task. You can never tell until the ferment has worked whether you succeeded in cleaning everything properly. I started the ferment right in the middle of an uncommonly hot few weeks, so finding a dark cool part of the house was a challenge.</p>
<p>The actual steps to take were very simple and there are a wide variety of videos online that you can watch to provide extra clues. When siphoning and bottling it would have been useful to have an extra pair of hands (or more sophisticated tools) but I muddled through.</p>
<p>At the stage of writing the beer has been bottled for five days. It will stay in the bottle for another two weeks to “condition”, which should add some carbonation and let the flavour mature and settle a bit. I am looking forward to seeing how it all turns out. Will it be drinkable?</p>
<hr />
<p>It’s been conditioning in the bottle for two weeks now and I opened one this evening to see how it was progressing. The taste was mildly hoppy but slightly “thin” somehow. There wasn’t as much carbonation as I’d hoped. I think I may have put too little sugar in the bottles before capping them. But still pretty drinkable, and should be better again in a week’s time.</p>
<hr />
<p>Taste number two, about five days later, and things seemed much better — either because I had lower expectations or because more time means better flavour. I’m happy to let others taste it now.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Fri, 23 Aug 2013 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2013-08-23-a-new-yeast-project-brewing.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Minor road accident on the way home</title>
    <link>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2013-08-17-minor-road-accident-on-the-way-home.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>Nearly two weeks ago I was cycling home from work, at most ten minutes away from the house, when I hit a car. The lights up ahead had changed to green and the vehicle in front moved away. My chain was making an odd noise so I looked down, which was my mistake.</p>
<p>According to the driver in front, a bus changed lanes in front and she slowed when I was expecting her to speed away. I slammed right into the back of the car, went over the top and hit my face on the boot. My right knee also hit the car and I still have some good discolouration there. Then I fell sideways — to my left, towards the pavement, thankfully — and crushed my shoulder under my full body weight. I have a thin scrape on my shoulder and a scab on the outside of my left knee. I think I hit my head on the road too, though my helmet has nothing to say on the matter. I certainly had a very sore neck for several days afterwards.</p>
<p>I was winded and numb down my left side for some time. The couple I had hit were very kind; definitely the nicest people I could hope to have been in an accident with. They loaded my bike into the boot and gave me a lift home.</p>
<p>I took the bike in for a service today and asked the mechanic to pay particular attention to the front wheel/forks. Other than the immediate issue of the impact it needed a thorough retune anyway. It’s clean and looks in good nick but it still picks up a fair amount of wear and tear.</p>
<p>And since I hit my head I should probably look at a replacement helmet. They’re supposed to be single-use items but it did its one job well.</p>
<p>I walked to work for the rest of the week, and since then I’ve been cycling more gingerly. In time I will get my confidence back and when I get my bike back from the shop I can hop on it with the knowledge that everything is working and ready to perform to the best of its abilities.</p>
<p>It’s an odd sensation being without a bike and watching many other people cycle past. I think I notice cyclists much more when I am walking — and more different types of cyclists too. I wonder what kind of cyclist I am? At the moment, the Recovering Cyclist.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sat, 17 Aug 2013 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2013-08-17-minor-road-accident-on-the-way-home.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>A wee tour round Islay</title>
    <link>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2013-08-06-a-wee-tour-round-islay.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>Between the end of term and the start of Helen’s elective we took a week’s holiday in Scotland on the bikes. We ferried and cycled from Ardrossan Harbour on the west coast, around the top of Arran, over to the Mull of Kintyre and then across from there to Islay.</p>
<p>We spent five days on Islay staying at <a href="http://www.dha-urlar-bed-and-breakfast.co.uk/" title="Dha Urlar bed &amp; breakfast">a B&amp;B in (well, near) Bowmore</a>, heading to different directions. Basically we spent five days doing as many distillery visits as we could get away with, which was pretty good fun to be honest. They’re interesting and — since it’s such a key part of Scottish culture and economy — it is worthwhile knowing how it actually works.</p>
<p>The places we visited were, in order, Bowmore, Bruichladdich, Ardbeg, Laphroaig and Caol Ila. There are eight distilleries on the island but we only managed to cover five of them. They’re not quite evenly distributed across the island — they tend to cluster near the main ports of Port Askaig in the north or Port Ellen in the south.</p>
<p>They all have their own selling point in terms of tradition — whether their barley is all grown on the island, or all Scottish; whether it’s all malted locally, or malted by hand; and so on for the peating, the milling, the material and antiquity of the mash tuns and washbacks, etc. You could make a very large multi-dimensional graph with this information! The one distillery that seems to do everything as traditionally as it is possible is Kilchoman, which we didn’t visit in the end. Something to return for!</p>
<p>Being on the bikes we didn’t have much scope for shopping. We bought a bottle of the Laphroaig Quarter Cask (aged in firkins for the greater area-to-volume ratio). Several of the tours also let you take your tasting glass away with you after the tour, so we’ve got a good set of those too!</p>
<p>The weather was clear and pleasant — open to the Atlantic as you would expect but not rain-lashed as we feared. Apart from a brief spell fighting against the wind when travelling from Ardbeg to Laphroaig along the south coast (and realising Helen had left her purse behind at the last distillery; the lovely woman at the visitor centre drove up to Ardbeg to collect it while we went on the tour) the weather worked entirely in our favour.</p>
<p>On the way through we stayed the night on Arran at Lochranza before getting the ferry in the morning. On the way home we did it all in one shot — leaving the bed and breakfast at 8.30 for the hour’s ride to Port Ellen and the ferry to Kennacraig. Then it was up the first brutal hill of the day and over to the other side of the peninsula for the ferry to Arran, the second brutal hill of the day around Arran and a terrifying ride down the other side to the gentle coastal route to Brodick ferry port and home. To fully assert our awesomeness we stopped off at a supermarket for a couple of drinks and went straight to a flat party instead of going home. (To be fair we didn’t even stay a full 2 hours but that’s not bad going.) The rest that night was good.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Tue, 06 Aug 2013 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2013-08-06-a-wee-tour-round-islay.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Cord&atilde;o de Ouro capoeira with CM Papa Leguas</title>
    <link>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2013-07-28-cdo-capoeira-with-cm-papa-leguas.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>Recently Contra Mestre Papa Leguas of Cordao de Ouro was invited to teach sessions in Edinburgh and Glasgow by <a href="http://www.cdoscotland.com/" title="Cordao de Ouro Scotland">CDO Scotland</a>. I attended one of the 3-hour classes in Glasgow to expand my experience a bit and see what other groups do when they’re being taught in their own style.</p>
<p>(I have previously been to large workshops organised by Malungos and Senzala but the guest teacher has been an Angola Mestre — Camaleao and Carlao respectively. This was a different circumstance because the teacher was definitely “something different”.)</p>
<p>The training room in Wellington Church on the corner of Southpark Avenue and University Avenue is a nice venue. Very clean and neat with some kind of textured vinyl-like flooring. I arrived and met a few people that I knew from training in Edinburgh and the regular open roda that we have to raise money for charity.</p>
<p>The class started with a discussion about body mechanics. The example was “to do an <em>au</em> you must throw your hips in the air, not put your hands on the ground” because “to do an <em>au sem mao</em> you must throw your hips in the air not throw your head at the ground” (paraphrased). I found this interesting and was looking forward to some biomechanical-oriented teaching which I think would help me a lot. Sadly it didn’t appear.</p>
<p>We did some plenary work on ginga and faking a rabo de arraia and spinning away again. Looking round the room I wasn’t the only person failing to see what he was actually doing, as he wasn’t describing the moves and he was executing them too fast to really follow.</p>
<p>This sequence built up into something longer, tacking on other moves which were also poorly understood. This was one of the defining moments of the class for me. Some of the sections were aimed at quite proficient players and the group as a whole didn’t reflect that. If it had been a trainers session rather than an open/all-levels session it would have been understandable.</p>
<p>The pairs work was similarly odd — maybe more for me than other people, I don’t know. I’m trying to be objective and subjective at the same time. Or at least subjective with the knowledge that I don’t want to come across as believing “they do it differently so they must be wrong”.</p>
<p>At the end was a split roda (one bateria, two simultaneous games) so everyone could have a few fun games to finish off. The music was something that took me a bit by surprise. The tempo was fast-paced and the singing didn’t match the rhythm at all. I think it would have been hard to match the speed of the bateria actually. This in particular was very alien to me.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 28 Jul 2013 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2013-07-28-cdo-capoeira-with-cm-papa-leguas.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Another rainy Traquair Fair</title>
    <link>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2013-07-28-another-rainy-traquair-fair.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>I’m just back from another Traquair Fair. I went to my first Traquair Fair two years ago and it rained quite heavily. There wasn’t one last year but in case I thought the 2011 rainfall was a freak occurence it happened again. Rain, wet tents, muddy dancing and drinking cider in the dark. We must be getting old though — no midnight trip to the maze.</p>
<p>We played some capoeira on the Saturday while the sun was beating down. We had a reasonable crowd at one point though they still wouldn’t “crowd” us. Even when we want them to form a tight circle around the action everyone hides off to the side. We need to concentrate on “street performance banter” to rally crowds and tell them what to do, where to sit and how to enjoy themselves. I think that would make for a more meaningful show.</p>
<p>So while we were programmed for a “Capoeira Dance Workshop” we ended up with a ninety minute capoeira game with some crowd interaction and an attempt to get people to clap or even sing. Enjoyable, especially on the lawn in the sun, in front of Traquair House, but not what it <em>could</em> have been.</p>
<p>The rains held off until we were finished and packing the instruments back up. The deluge when it came was pretty all-consuming though…</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 28 Jul 2013 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2013-07-28-another-rainy-traquair-fair.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Jurassic Park: airport fiction when dinosaurs ruled the bestsellers</title>
    <link>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2013-07-25-jurassic-park-airport-fiction.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>As a little chap I distinctly remember enjoying Jurassic Park on the big screen. I think it was one of those defining blockbuster movies of my youth, like everybody remembers seeing Star Wars for the first time. And in some sense it was just as revolutionary for the use of computer graphics. Those dinos looked <em>real!</em></p>
<p>The book is a proper disappointment, falling squarely into the category of stories that get much better when translated to film. Michael Crichton was a prolific writer of works that would eventually get adapted to the screen — maybe they all needed someone else to clean up his terrible dialogue?</p>
<p>Whenever I read a book now I come back to Christopher Brookmyre’s BDQ:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>I’ll swallow any scenario, as long as the film sticks to its own bullet-deadliness quotient.</p>
<p>An action film establishes its own rules of gunplay. In some, every bullet is potentially lethal — even the old shot to the shoulder can look worryingly near to the upper-chest area. But in others, machine guns can seem the least deadly weapon known to man. To illustrate, at one end of the spectrum there’s your Tarantino movies: reputations aside, there’s not that much gunplay, so when somebody lets off a shot, it’s for real, and it’s usually fatal. High bullet-deadliness quotient. At the other end, there’s your John Woo movies: zillions of rounds goin’ off an’ the only thing they ever hit is glass. Low bullet-deadliness quotient. In a high BDQ film, if the baddie draws a bead on somebody, get ready for ketchup. In a low BDQ film, that’s just a bad day for the janitor. And both types are fine by me, as long as the rules are followed consistently.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The issue of consistency in suspension of disbelief is paramount. It is the downfall of many a bad movie. <em>Prometheus</em>, for example, repeatedly set up characters as leaders in their field who made basic mistakes. in a high technology world which was simultaneously less capable than our own.</p>
<p>Jurassic Park has these failings and more besides. There are a number of “experts” in paleontology, genetics, mathematics and zoo management who have manage to come out with some real howlers. Geneticists who can’t remember where they got their DNA from. Park management who can’t remember how to reboot the park management system after it fails.</p>
<p>What really gets my goat is the inconsistency in character. From one scene to the next characters will change personality drastically so that the stupid thing they do to move the plot along seems reasonable. The nine year-old girl who was rocking back and forth in terror is now complaining about lack of ice cream or wanting to play with the walkie-talkie. In case it had escaped your attention there’s a velociraptor in the hallway. But the plot dictates the raptor find the kids so rather than stay quiet and frightened they have to squabble over who gets to play with this new toy.</p>
<p>This inconsistency appears again and again, and each time it does the urge to fling the book across the room rises. Frankly, they should all have been eaten.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Thu, 25 Jul 2013 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2013-07-25-jurassic-park-airport-fiction.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>First time taking a capoeira class</title>
    <link>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2013-07-18-first-time-taking-a-capoeira-class.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>Today, through an unfortunate series of events, both Piolho and Nick were unavailable to teach the class — Piolho we knew all along wouldn’t make it but Nick had to work late out of town.</p>
<p>The unfortunate part comes where not one but two new people arrive at the group. I ended up leading most of the class with some aid from Simon and Stephen. On the bright side new folk were from the Glasgow Senzala group and had done capoeira before. Everyone was able to follow along with my garbled instructions and wooly attempts to explain.</p>
<p>Most of the class was spent going over very basic stuff which was nice. They were used to a different kind of capoeira, so they could use that to get familiar with the style and I wasn’t too taxed coming up with crazy sequences and variations. We spent a good amount of time on the ginga, because it’s something we all need to work on, endlessly, and it’s something that is very different between Senzala and Mao No Chao.</p>
<p>In the end I enjoyed myself and I think everyone felt they had worked up a good sweat and didn’t seem too angry that they weren’t getting a teacher with a plan and a system!</p>
<p>The class was the opposite of what I’d been looking forward to, as I’d wanted to work more on the music stuff and had been trying to practise a basic samba rhythm on the pandeiro while waiting outside. But that is not how things fell out.</p>
<p>So I hope to see them again in future and if I ever have to teach a class again I’ll maybe have something in the back of my mind.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Thu, 18 Jul 2013 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2013-07-18-first-time-taking-a-capoeira-class.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Cooking by ratios: the book</title>
    <link>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2013-07-13-cooking-by-ratios-the-book.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>I’m not a great cook and very much envy the just-throw-stuff-together style of cookery which some people have. The exacting sciences of mixed drinks and bread baking provide some solace for me, because they’re all about the correct mixing of ingredients in well defined ratios.</p>
<p>It seems obvious that a book called <em>Ratio: The Simple Codes Behind the Craft of Everyday Cooking</em> would be something right up my street. Michael Ruhlman attempts to argue that much more of cooking follows rules of proportion and ratio — and that lack of emphasis on this fact leaves people slavishly following recipes without understanding the fundamentals. Each subtle variation is a “new” recipe.</p>
<p><em>Ratio</em> is his solution: a book of recipes by proportion. His introduction stipulates the important rule that ratios should be understood by weight not volume because the quantity of dry ingredients will vary a lot when packed. The cornflakes rule: contents may settle during transit.</p>
<p>We’re barely out of the starting blocks before he starts breaking his rules. Flour in cups, butter in sticks (what?), broccoli in cups…</p>
<p>Then we get to the cake chapter and he flat out says — the ratio isn’t important! The proportions of sponge and pound cake are identical! So we’re less than a fifth into the book and he’s already working hard to demolish his whole argument.</p>
<p>I didn’t follow any of the recipes though some of them looked dubious. Other people who read the book before me thought his pastry was totally wrong. But right or not, I didn’t come away feeling that I understood the ingredients at any deeper level. His recipes were just as confusing as if they’d been given as predefined measures. Apart from a dartboard-style diagram on the front cover there weren’t any useful charts to explain how the recipes related to each other and the proportions and ingredients used.</p>
<p>Starting again from scratch — with a more technical approach to the subject and a more discriminating eye for the examples — and this book could be a real winner. I really wanted to like it, but so many things annoyed me.</p>
<p>To take a contrasting example, <em>Dough</em> by Richard Bertinet uses the same approach to ratios but devotes an entire book to (in essence) just one ratio: ten parts flour to seven parts water. In <em>Dough</em> the technical detail is omitted because there are so many examples. <em>Ratio</em> has neither technical explanation nor deep coverage, but instead flits from chapter to chapter.</p>
<p>If there are other treatments of this topic out there I would be interested to hear what they’re like.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sat, 13 Jul 2013 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://dougalstanton.net/posts/2013-07-13-cooking-by-ratios-the-book.html</guid>
</item>

    </channel> 
</rss>
